[Phone rings]
[Tommy] Hello?
[Branch]‘Hey, guys. It’s John Branch from “The NY Times”.
嗨，哥们，我是《纽约时报》的John Branch
‘How’s it going up there?’
你们怎样？
[Tommy] Good, John.
挺好，John
[Branch]‘How high up are you guys right now?’
哥们，你们现在位置多高？
[Tommy] We are about 1,200 feet up the wall at our base camp.
我们在1200英尺高的黎明墙（Dawn Wall）基地大本营
This has been our home for nine days now.
目前也是我们九天中的家
[Branch]‘Tommy, I guess the bottom line question here,
Tommy，我想问，最根本的是
‘why are you doing this?
为何你们这么做？
‘What’s the point of all this for you?’
对于你们这意味着什么？
[Presenter 1] On the air tonight with a story of two men
今晚的故事是，空中的两位
attempting to free climb the famously steep face
正在著名的加州优胜美地国家公园 （Yosemite ）陡峭的El Capitan 岩墙 (世界上最大单体花岗岩)
of El Capitan in Yosemite.
进行徒手攀岩
[Presenter 2]
Inch by nerve-racking inch,
一英寸接着恼人的一英寸
using only their fingertips to grasp razor sharp edges.
用他们的指尖去抓握住刀片般的锋利岩石边缘
[Presenter 3]Tommy Caidwell and Kevin Jorgeson
Tommy Caidwell和 Kevin Jorgeson
attempt the hardest climb in the world.
在进行世上最艰难的攀岩
[Presenter 4] No one has ever free-climbed the Dawn Wall.
从未有人徒手攀爬过黎明墙 （the Dawn Wall）
[Presenter 5] 3,000 feet of straight-up granite.
它是3000英尺高、直上直下的单体花岗岩
[Presenter 6] A climb watched by the world.
这次攀岩,全球都在观看中
[Presenter 7]  These guys have captured the world’s attention.
他们俩也吸引了全球关注
[Presenter 8] They’re trying to make history.
他们想要创造历史
[Presenter 9] El Capitan’s infamous Dawn Wall.
El Capitan 名声在外的黎明墙
[Mom]As a kid, Tommy was slow at everything.
Tommy 从小就样样迟缓
He had a lot of difficulty in school.
他在学校也有挺多困难
The teachers actually at one point told us
老师有次告诉我们
that he was mentally retarded and would never learn.
他可能智力迟缓，很难学会什么
I was developmentally delayed through... probably still.
我一直都发展延迟 ......可能都静止了
I was this very fragile little kid
打小就很脆弱
incredibly shy.
还异常羞怯
But meanwhile, my dad was, like, the symbol of a man.
与此同时，我老爸却是人中龙凤
He was this big bodybuilder dude and mountain climber.
他是大大有名的健美明星和登山选手
Larger than life.
生活的强者
[Dad]Tommy was small.
Tommy 那时很小
He was way behind.
远远落在别人后面
Didn’t crawl until he was over two.
两岁多才学会爬着走
[Tommy] I think my dad felt
我猜我老爹是这么想的：
the best way to prepare this fragile little kid for the world
培养这个脆弱小仔的最好方法是
was to toughen him up a little bit.
要对他严厉一点
So he took me on all these adventures.
所以他带着我去参加所有的冒险运动
[Dad]Three years old, strap on the skis.
三岁时，被困在滑雪中
[Tommy] Camping in a snow cave during a blizzard.
暴风雪期间，也到雪窟里去露营
Every summer, we’d go to Yosemite with my family,
每年夏天，全家一起去优胜美地
and my dad would take me climbing on these giant walls.
我老爹就带我去爬那些巨大的岩墙
Some of the craziest climbing stunts you could ever do
有些最惊人的攀岩特技，别人不敢做的
and he did it with a six-year-old.
他让六岁的我去做。
[Kelly]The things that Tommy’s dad took him on,
Tommy 老爹带他做的那些动作，
today you would have Child Protective Services
到如今看，儿童保护中心
coming after you.
都会在身后来追诉的
He basically took hardship and rephrased it as growth.
他本质上就是把艰难困苦，演绎为成长中的一环
[Tommy]He was loving, but he definitely let me suffer.
我老爹很萌，不过他铁了心是要让我吃些苦的。
The word that was in my mind was resilience.
在我心里，那个词叫做弹性。
It seems to me one of the best gifts you can give your kid
对我而言，给子女最好的礼物，
is an ability to deal with adversity.
莫过于处于逆境时的应对能力
[Tommy] By the time I was 14 or 15,
当我14或15岁时
there was climbs that I could do that my dad couldn’t.
有一场攀岩比赛，我可以参加，我老爹不可以
[Dad]Tommy’s strong.
Tommy很强大的
[Tommy]Climbing was the first thing in my life
攀岩是我生命的头等大事
where I could stand out a little bit.
因为我可以比别人强出去一点点
[Mom] Airight. Woo!
好棒
[Dad]So Tommy was 16,
Tommy16岁时，
and Snowbird held the Snowbird Invitational that year.
雪鸟城组织举行了一场雪鸟邀请赛
[Tommy]This big climbing competition.
那是一次大型攀岩竞赛
We thought we’d drive over there and watch the comp
我们本以为就是开车去看比赛的
and get some autographs.
得到一些签名
[Tommy] We just went there to be fans, really.
真是，本来准备去当粉丝的
[Dad] And the day before the big competition,
结果，大赛的前一天
they had a Citizens’ Comp that anybody who shows up can enter.
他们在Citizens' Comp会议上决定，任何去现场的都可以参赛
[Tommy] So I entered that, my first competition ever.
所以，我就参加了。我的平生第一次参赛
[Dad]Well, Tommy won.
昂，Tommy 赢了比赛
And I don’t know if this was an official policy
我不知这是不是官方规则
or just something they dreamt up on the spot,
还是当场他们随意的决定
but they asked Tommy
那会儿他们问Tommy
if he wanted to enter the World Invitational the next day.
他能否参加第二天的世界邀请赛
Hello, everyone. I’m James Brown,
大家好，我是James Brown
and welcome to Snowbird, Utah,
欢迎来到犹他州的雪球城
for the International Sport Climbing Championship.
观看国际体育攀岩冠军杯赛
[Presenter] Expert climbers will test their skills
专业攀岩者将运用他们的技术
against a man-made 120-foot wall.
攀爬120英尺的人造岩体
[Dad] There were 12 competitors.
总共有12名参赛者
-[Tommy]The icons of climbing.
-[Dad]and it was so intimidating.
攀岩图标
很吓人
[Tommy] Nobody had ever heard of me.
那时没人知晓我
I was just this scrawny little kid.
我只是一个瘦弱的小孩
I was videoing Tommy as he goes climbing up this thing.
Tommy攀爬时，我在给他录像
[Dad] Come on, Tommy.
加油，Tommy
[Dad] He got past the final roof.
他越过了最后的终点
So Tommy’s winning.
Tommy是冠军
[Man]Airight, Tommy!
Tommy，真棒
And I started shaking.
我都发抖了
I just dropped the camera.
摄像机也摔掉了下去
I mean I completely lost it.
呃，我意思是，我整个没抓住摄像机。
[Dad]Tommy got to the top.
Tommy到达顶端终点时
The only climber to complete this climb.
是唯一一个完成全部攀岩的选手
So all of a sudden,
Tommy went from nobody at all
Tommy从默默无闻
to winner of Snowbird
变成雪鸟城的攀岩冠军
[Mom] I mean, that was just unbelievable.
真是不可思议
It changed his whole life.
完全改变了他的生命
[KeIIy] Tommy became known
Tommy变成了
as one of the best young climbers.
最佳的年轻攀岩家之一
But he didn’t grow up
但，他并没有
the way most of us do.
以我们一般成长的方式长大
Through high school he didn’t have girlfriends.
整个高中时期，他没有女友
He didn’t have a social life. He just went climbing.
他没有社交圈生活。他就是一个劲的攀岩
[PA, indistinctl
[Tommy] I was doing this series of competitions,
在一系列的攀岩竞赛中
and I met this girl, Beth.
我遇到了Beth
She just caught my attention totally. I was like, “Woah!”
老天，她完全吸引住我
Tommy just had this really big, goofy, endearing grin.
Tommy笑容灿烂、笨拙、隐忍
We both lived and breathed climbing.
我们俩都以攀岩为生命
[KeIIy] Tommy’s this climbing savant,
Tommy有了攀岩同伴专家
and then he meets Beth, the female version of himself.
他遇见Beth，就像遇见他自己的女性版
He’s head over heels.
简直喜不自禁
[Tommy] I just found ways to go wherever she was.
只要她去的地方，我都设法过去
-OK?
-Yeah.
[Tommy] I found out she was going to Yosemite,
我发现她要去优胜美地
so I followed her out there.
就一路追随过去
We ended up climbing a big wall together.
我们一起攀爬完成一块大岩墙
You know, we were next to each other all the time.
是呀，我们一直并肩攀爬
24 hours a day together.
24小时在一起
[Beth]Sleeping 1,000 feet off the ground on this portaledge,
睡在离地1000英尺的半空中，在可折叠悬挂帐篷里
which is like a hanging cot.
就像是悬挂式的小床
[Tommy]  You sleep head to toe. There’s just more room that way.
如果头脚接踵的话，也还有一点空间
So I laid down,
所以我躺下了
and she laid down the same way that I was,
她也像我一样躺下
with her head at the same end.
头并头地躺下
And I was pretty excited by this.
当时我特别激动
I was like “Ooh, goodness. This is getting exciting.”
我想，老天，真是太兴奋了
I just hadn’t been in love before,
之前我从没有爱过谁
and I just fell hardcore, right off the bat.
那个瞬间，立刻就陷入了
[Beth] It just clicked.
就是来电的感觉
We had so many dreams of traveling and climbing together.
我们拥有如此多的梦想：一起旅行一起攀岩
And then we got invited to go on a big adventure trip.
之后，我们受到邀请
An expedition to Kyrgyzstan.
去参加在吉尔吉斯斯坦的一次野外探险旅行
Kyrgyzstan is this beautiful, mountainous country
吉尔吉斯斯坦是个多山的美丽国家
in Central Asia.
在亚洲中部
We’d seen pictures from friends that had been there,
我们曾经看到过一些朋友去后拍摄的图片
and it looked like a paradise for climbers.
对于攀岩选手，那里简直就是天堂。
I was a photographer working in the outdoor industry.
我是一名户外摄影家
And this amazing opportunity came about for me
当时接到一个灰常棒的机会
to shoot an expedition with Beth and Tommy and Jason.
与Beth、Tommy和Jason一起远行，给他们做拍摄
We were just four young climbers looking for a big adventure
我们是四个喜欢探险的
in a new and unusual part of the world.
喜欢在世界上新的地点、不同寻常的地点去做攀岩的年轻人
[Tommy] We charter a helicopter into the Kara-Su Valley.
我们包了一架直升机，来到Kara-Su山谷
Unbelievably beautiful.
美丽到难以置信
Just felt like a dream come true,
感觉梦想成真
out in the middle of this adventure
一边探险
with this girl that I was totally in love with.
一边与我深爱的女孩在一起
A week-and-a-half into our trip,
出行一周半以后的一天
the four of us were sleeping in portaledges
我们四个正睡在悬挂式野营帐篷里时
1,000 feet up the wall,
高度是在岩壁的1000英尺处
-and we wake up to gunshots...
-[Gunshot]
我们被枪声惊醒
...these piercing, close gunshots.
子弹的穿透声，越来越近
[Gunshots]
The bullets hitting the wall right between our portaledges.
子弹击中了我们几个悬挂帐篷之间的岩石
We’re sitting there like,
我们坐在那里
“Oh, my God, we’re getting shot at.”
老天，难道我们要被打中吗
And you can’t run away. You can’t do anything.
可是，既无法逃跑，也无法做任何其它事
We’re just sitting ducks up here.
就像别人的靶子，只能坐在那儿
We look down, and you could see these figures.
我们往下看，可以看到这些人影
[Tommy] These guys waving at us to come down.
他们朝我们挥手示意我们下去
[Beth]We rappelled down to the ground.
我们靠绳索下降
[Tommy] We’re encountered by four guys, heavily armed.
下去以后，见到四个全副武装的人
[John] They took us to our base camp.
他们把我们弄到我们的攀岩大本营
[Jason] All of our tents were cut open.
我们的帐篷全部被割开
A lot of our food was splayed around the meadow.
许多我们的食品被撒落在四周的草地上
They had us start hiding our camp.
他们让我们把帐篷藏起来
And so suddenly, it hits us, we’re hostages right now.
这时我们才醒悟到，自己是人质
[Beth] Later, we learned that these guys
之后，我们知道这些人
were part of the Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan,
是乌兹别克斯坦的伊斯兰运动组织成员
these rebels that wanted to overthrow the government.
他们目标是推翻政府
[John] We were caught up in this battle
我们被卷入这场
between these rebels and the Kyrgyz military.
吉尔吉斯军队与叛军之间的争战
[Tommy] All of a sudden,
突然之间
Kyrgyz military helicopters started to fly over,
吉尔吉斯军队的直升机在头顶盘旋
soldiers show up on the hillside,
山坡上也有士兵出现
-and this battle breaks out. 争战开始
-[Gunfire]
The rebels start pointing their guns at us, yelling. “Hide!”
叛军用枪指着我们吼道：躲起来
Then we dive in these trees.
我们就躲避到树林里
[John] The rebels had taken a Kyrgyz soldier hostage.
叛军也抓吉尔吉斯士兵的人质
They took the other captive.
他们把抓到的其他俘虏
And they just shot him in the head.
在脑袋上直接给一枪
[Gunshot]
I just remember shaking uncontrollably
记得我那时，不由自主地颤抖
and Tommy just holding me as tight as he could.
Tommy紧紧地抱着我
Are they just going to kill us next?
他们会不会下次就枪杀我们？
[Distant gunfire]
[Tommy] Once it’s dark, the gunfire dies down.
天黑以后，枪击声消退了
And the rebels start marching us through the mountains.
叛军押着我们穿过山脉
It’s four rebels, the four of us.
叛军是四个，我们也是四个
It’s really cold. We’re 11,000 feet in elevation.
超级冷。我们在海拔11000英尺的高地上
We don’t have warm clothes.
没有暖和的衣服
We don’t have any food.
也没有任何食物
[Beth] We had no idea where we were going.
我们都不知道会去哪里
[John] We would hike through the night,
要徒步穿过黑夜
and then during the day, they would hide us.
天明以后，他们就藏起我们
[Beth] They hid us in the craziest spots.
他们把我们藏身在一些难以想象的地方
[Tommy] Burying us in holes in the ground
比如地下的洞穴里
so that we wouldn’t be seen by the military.
这样政府军就不会看到我们
[John] This went on for six days.
就这样过了六天
[Beth] Day two or three, hunger really started to set in.
从第二或第三天开始，饥饿就击倒了我们
[Tommy] You know, we’re sort of just wasting away.
你明白的，我们变得特消瘦
[Beth]  I thought they’re taking us back to their base
我以为他们要把我们带回基地
or they’re taking us somewhere, there’s a purpose to this.
或者带到什么地方，总之有一个目的地
[John] Finally, we realized
最后，我们意识到
they were leading us in a giant circle.
他们就是带着我们兜了一个大圈子
Like, these guys clearly don’t have a plan.
就是说，这些人根本就没有啥计划。
Jason and John started to scheme about how we could get away.
Jason 和John开始思量该怎么逃脱
I mean, things were getting super desperate.
我意思是，情形变得超级绝望
They were ready to take matters into their own hands.
他们预备把形势掌控到自己手上
At one point, two of our captors left.
在某个地点，抓捕我们的人，其中有两个离开了。
-We never saw them again.
-[Gunshots]
自后再也未见过他们
We found out later that they got killed.
然后才发现他们被打死了
On our sixth night of captivity,
所以在被抓捕后的第六天
the two captors that were remaining with us
剩下两个抓捕我们的人
decided that one of them would go in one direction
决定其中一个人应该
to try and get some food
沿着一个方向去找吃的
and then we would head off with the other one.
我们这些人，就和另一个抓捕者一起走。
[John] So we get left alone with the one rebel,
那时，押解我们的就只有一个人了
climbing up this cliff side.
他把我们押着爬上悬崖边。
We were comfortable on the terrain, and he was not.
我们是很习惯这种悬崖地形的，而叛军不是
If we’re going to escape, this is the opportunity.
如果企图逃脱，这是绝好机会
[Tommy] Jason and John decided
Jason 和John 开始决定
they would try and push our remaining captor off this cliff
他们想把这个留守的抓捕者推下悬崖
and then run away.
然后逃跑
[Jason]John and I were trying to look for a point
Jason 和我开始找合适的地点
that we could throw him off.
让我们可以推他下悬崖
[John]But we kept going and kept going.
但我们一直走啊走
We just couldn’t quite push him.
没法一下子就推下他
[Tommy] As we got to the top,
等我们到达山顶
I realized that our opportunity was going to be over.
我觉得我们的机会已经过去了
And I decided that this was what I had to do.
因此我认为这事应该由我去做
I had to go and I needed to push this guy off this cliff
我想跑走，所以就需要把他推下悬崖
in order to save our lives.
这样我们才能得救
Tommy came over to me at this point, and he said,
Tommy 就过来问我
“Do you think I should do this?”
“你觉得是不是我应该去做？”
I was thinking, “Yes, no, yes, no.”
我想，是的，不是，是的，不是
So I just didn’t say anything.
却一个字也没有说出来
[Tommy] I took that as that she would be OK with it.
我把Beth的沉默看成是她默许这个事
So I just ran up behind him
所以就跑在叛军解押者的后面
and I put one hand on his back and grabbed his gun strap.
往他后背推了一掌，同时抓住他的枪带
And my other hand went on his chest
我另一只手伸向他的胸部
and I just gave a push...
推了一下
...to send him flying off this cliff.
把他推翻飞下悬崖
We saw him hit a ledge,
我们看见他摔倒在伸出的一块平整岩石上
bounce off of it, and just fall out of sight into the darkness.
被重新弹出，然后就摔进黑暗，再也看不到了
[Beth]
Tommy completely broke down,
Tommy整个人都崩溃了
had his head in his arms and he was crying.
头埋进胳膊开始哭
[Tommy] I couldn’t believe what I had just done.
无法相信自己的所作所为
I had just killed somebody.
无法相信自己杀了人
The whole world came crashing down on me all at once.
片刻之间，整个世界都压倒了我
[Beth] We were all trying to reassure him and say that,
我们大家都使劲肯定Tommy的行为
“You’re not a bad person, you just saved our lives.”
都说，你不是坏人，是你才救了我们
[Tommy] They really tried to comfort me.
大家都尝试着安慰我
But there was a sense of urgency that we better get going,
但，当时最紧迫的是需要跑出来
because we didn’t know if the other captor was gonna show up.
因为我们不知道那个另外的叛军解押是否会出现
[John] We knew from hiking in earlier
早先在徒步探险时，我们知道
where there was a military outpost we could try and run to.
有一支政府警戒分队（在附近），我们可以跑去求助
[Beth] So even on almost no food for six days,
这样，尽管饿了六天
adrenaline kicked in.
肾上腺还是刺激了身体
[Jason]
So we ran for four hours.
我们因此一口气跑了四个小时
Through the darkness down this valley.
穿过黑暗，下到山谷
[Beth] We were greeted by this man yelling at us with this gun.
之后有一个人用枪指着我们，对我们大喊大叫
[John] Throw up our hands, start yelling that we’re Americans.
我们举起手，也开始大喊，说我们是美国人
[Beth] And luckily, it was the Kyrgyz army.
幸运的是，这是吉尔吉斯斯坦部队
This huge wave of relief came over us.
获释的巨大喜悦汹涌而至
This horrible situation that we had been in was over.
我们经历的恐怖状况总算过去
They gave us food and water, military fatigues.
他们给了我们这些逃难者一些东西吃喝
And then we got helicoptered out from there.
再之后，我们乘直升机离开那里。
[Presenter]  From our studios in New York, here’s Jane Pauley.
Jane Pauley 在纽约工作室报道
[Jane] Four young Americans face a life or death choice,
四位年轻的美国人面对生死选择
with the ultimate question, to kill or be killed?
终极问题是，杀人还是被杀
[Tommy] When we got home, there was this crazy media circus.
回到家中，狂热的媒体包围过来
You guys are walking with this captor
你们和这个抓捕人一起
on a very rocky cliff.
走过岩石丛生的悬崖
Tell me what you did, Tommy.
Tommy，和我说说发生了什么
We just ended up pushing the guy.
我们就是把他推下去了
-You pushed him over the cliff.
-Yeah.
你把他推下了悬崖 ----- 是
What happened at that moment when you realized,
那一刻，当你意识到
I’ve actually done this, I’ve killed somebody?
我真的这么做了，我杀死了人，到底发生了什么？
I thought that I was an evil person. I said to Beth,
我对Beth说，觉得自己是个罪人
“How can you love me after I did something like this?”
这件事后，你还能爱我吗？
And, uh...
唉
[Dad] After Kyrgyzstan,
从吉尔吉斯斯坦事件以后
Tommy had tremendous personality changes.
Tommy的性格大变
Speaking so softly.
说话变得轻声
I was like, what is inside me that allowed me to do this?
我在想，自己内心里面到底是什么允许自己这么做的？
Just an entirely different person.
完全是一个不同的人
[John Long] Yosemite is known
优胜美地
as the Mecca of world rock climbing.
对于世界攀岩者来说，是可仰慕的朝圣地
And the crown jewel of this Mecca is El Capitan.
而朝圣地的皇冠珍宝是El Capitan岩壁
It’s just this iconic 3,000 foot high monolith.
它是标志性级别的3000英尺高的单体花岗岩
When you see that thing for the first time,
若是第一次看见它，
it takes your breath away.
你会摒住呼吸
The steepest, blankest, most forlorn...
最陡峭、最荒芜、最孤独的
impressive part of El Cap
El Capitan 的那一处
is the Dawn Wall.
就是the Dawn Wall (黎明墙）
People have done a handful of free climbs up El Cap
人们曾经无数次尝试徒手攀登El Capitan
to the right and to the left.
从右侧或左侧
But the Dawn Wall has never been climbed.
但，黎明墙，至今无人徒手攀爬上去过。
Just the sheer magnitude of blank rock on the thing,
纯粹是巨大的一块大岩石
it just looks impossible.
完全是一种不可能
Until Tommy CaIdwell came along,
直到Tommy Caldwell攀登以前
nobody had actually considered trying it.
此前，没有人真正考虑徒手攀爬过
If Tommy and his partner Kevin can actually do this,
如果Tommy和他的搭档Kevin 可以做到
it will be the most continuously difficult rock climb ever done.
那意味着，人类终于把这一块难以克服的岩石给制服了
Nothing else is even close to it.
不过从目前说，还无人接近这个目标
[Tommyl It’s December 27th,
12月27日
and we’re planning on heading up for like two weeks plus.
我们已经花两周多时间，计划出发了
We’ll see.
我们要等看结果
The goal is climb it in a single push,
目标是一次性攀爬
which means we’re going to leave the ground,
换言之，我们从离开地面算起
live on the wall,
中间住在岩壁上
and not come down until we’re done.
直到成功登顶后，方可下岩
[Kevin] We’re going for it.
我们准备出发
I’m nervous.
有点儿紧张
We’ve put in so much work leading up to this moment.
为了这一刻，已经准备了许久的工作
There’s nothing left to do but take a couple deep breaths
别的都可以了，只需深吸一口气
and start climbing.
开始攀登
Day one. 第一日
Yup.对
This is going to be awesome.
很惊人呐
[Long] The Dawn Wall itself is 3,000 feet tall.
黎明墙本身有3千英尺高
The route that they think they have figured out
他们思考过的可能途径
is comprised of 32 individual pitches.
总共有32个独立绳距
Each pitch is its own challenge,like the stages of a race.
每一个绳距都是挑战，就是像进入比赛场地
A pitch is a rope-length long, about 150 feet or so.
一个绳距的意思是，大约150尺长短，就是一根绳子的大概长度
And ends of the ledge
在（绳距的）末尾平台部分
are a natural resting place on the rock.
是岩石上天然的休息处
[Tommy] Yeah, man. Good work.
哥们，厉害。干的棒
[Long] When you end the pitch,
当你完成一个绳距时
you anchor yourself to the wall...
就可以在岩墙上挂锚
[kevin] One down, thirty-something to go.
一个再下去，大概三十尺左右
[Long] ...and hold the rope or belay as your partner comes up.
然后抓住绳子，或者栓在系绳栓上，等待同伴上来
Once you’ve both done that pitch without falling,
如果两个攀岩者都没有失手，完成一个绳距后
you can move on to the next pitch.
方可继续下一个绳距
When you’re free-climbing,
如果你是徒手抱石攀岩
you’re using your hands and feet
你需要用到双手与双脚
to climb the natural features on the rock
攀爬岩石上自然的裂缝
without any assistance from the rope.
并不依赖绳子的任何辅助
-[Kevin]Good job.
-[Tommy]Yeah, man.
真棒，是的，哥们
[Long] You take turns leading each pitch
双方换位攀爬绳距
placing protection in the cracks to catch you in case you fall.
在岩缝中安置保护装置，用以防止摔落
[Tommy] Yeah, come on. You got it.
加油，哥们你行的
Ugh! Oh! 糟
[Tommy] If you fall, 一旦摔落
you just go back down to the beginning of that pitch,
就需要退回到那个绳距的原点
and then the other guy tries it.
等另一位尝试
[Long] They have a certain number of pitches
他们有一串绳距
they’re trying to get through each day
每天要完成一些
to stay on track to finish this climb.
留在攀爬途径上做完本次攀爬
The first few pitches are relatively easy.
开头的几个绳距比较容易
But as you get higher on the wall...
但当攀爬越高
...the wall gets steeper,
岩壁越陡峭
the holes get smaller,
（岩点）石洞越小
and the climbing gets way more difficult.
攀岩的困难程度就越大
[Kevin] It’s hard to articulate
很难表达清楚
the level of detail that’s required.
所需的具体水准
You can’t make any mistake in where you grab the hold
当你抓抱住岩石时，不能有任何差错
and how you place your toe.
还要明了怎样安放自己的脚趾位置
You’re pushing and pulling as hard as you possibly can,
竭尽全力去推和拉
always on the verge of slipping off.
永远都在坠落的边缘
Argh! 啊
[Tommy] Oh, no! 天呐
-[Kevin]Oh!
-[Tommy]Oh, foot slip.
脚滑
[Kevin] We climb all day into the night,
我们从白天爬到晚上
trying the same pitch until we both do it.
在同一个绳距上各自尝试，相互完成
Come on, Tommy!
加油，Tommy
Come on!
加油
[Tommy] Man, I’m getting tired.
哥们，真累了。
[Kevin] Tommy is just a man possessed.
Tommy 这个人很执着
Come on. Finish this.
加油，完成它
Yeah, come on.
对，加油
Yeah, man. 对，哥们
Yee-hoo! 啊哈
And I’m just trying to keep up.
我尽力保持住
[Tommy] You got it, Kevin. Come on!
Kevin，你完成了，加油
Come on! Come on! Come on! 加油
Yeah, that was awesome, dude.
啊，真棒
[Kevin] Thank God I didn’t fall.
感谢上帝，这次没掉下来
[Tommy] Nice, man. 棒
[Long] When you’re trying a big wall like this,
当你尝试这样的大岩壁时
the work does not end
事儿是没完没了的
once the climbing is done at the end of the day.
每一天完成攀爬以后
You’ve got to haul up hundreds of pounds of gear,
就需要把几百磅重的器械拉上去
set up portaledges...
架起悬空帐篷
[Tommy] This seems pretty good. Pretty flat, even, I would say.
瞅瞅，看起来挺棒。还挺平
[Long]
...and gag down some food.
然后吞吃一些食物
[Tommy] I actually brought a bag of kale on the wall
事实上，我带上去了一袋子的甘蓝
to put it in our burritos. Mmh!
可以放在卷饼一起吃
This is the hardest thing you could ever do on your fingers,
这是你可以用自己手指完成的最难的事儿了
climbing this route.
要完成这个途径
It’s just grabbing razor blades.
就仿佛是去抓住剃刀刀片
I tape up any wounds with Neosporin for healing.
我用Neosporin消炎膏包扎伤口
Then I wake up probably twice in the night and reapply.
夜里可能需要醒两次重新上药
Getting pretty obsessed with my lips.
嘴唇也超级难受
[Long] Then you’ve got to hope you can get a little sleep.
你才希望能睡个好觉时
The next day is going to be more of the same, but harder.
其实第二天将会差不多，还愈发艰难
And it’s going to go on day after day,
天天如此
two weeks, three weeks. Nobody knows.
两周，三周，没人知道（多久可以完成）
[Tommy] After Kyrgyzstan,
吉尔吉斯斯坦事件以后
we’re trying to absorb what had happened.
我们一直想忍受住发生的经过
Beth is really traumatized.
Beth 饱受心灵创伤
[Beth]I started to have nightmares and couldn’t sleep.
开始连着做噩梦，无法入眠
I did not want to be separated from Tommy at that point.
我不希望在那个时刻离开Tommy
[Tommy] Beth and I are bonded at the hip. I’m her rock.
Beth和我在同一险境，我就是她的岩石
We go to church a few times.
我们一起上教堂好几次
We hadn’t been to church in ten years.
过去十年间，我们都没有去过教堂
We’re just searching. We’re like, what does this mean?
我们在探究，这到底是为什么
We go to a therapist.
后来去看了一位心理治疗专家
It’s like nobody knows how to deal with this situation.
貌似没有人知道怎样才能更好面对这种状态
I think my way of dealing with it was
我想我自己的面对方式是
you just get back on that horse and go climb again.
再次回到攀岩
This has always been my safe place,
它一直是我的安全伞
my way to deal with life.
是我面对生活的路途
I didn’t know what to think about Kyrgyzstan.
我不知道怎样去思考吉尔吉斯斯坦事件
Part of me was feeling kind of empowered.
部分的自我，感受到某种神授
I was like, when the shit really hit the fan,
就像是，如果真的麻烦上头时
I was able to do what needed to be done
也不得不去做应当做的事
to get us out of there.
把自己救出困境
[Beth] Tommy jumped right back into climbing,
Tommy 很快就回到攀岩
and slowly we got back into our groove.
慢慢地，我们回到了常规
[Tommy] We’re both professional rock climbers,
我们俩都是职业攀岩者
doing these really cool climbs all over the place.
在许多地方完成了这些酷酷的攀爬
[Beth] He started setting these lofty goals.
他开始设立宏大的理想
[Tommy] Trying to climb harder and harder routes.
试图攀爬那些难而又难的路径
And then, about a year after Kyrgyzstan,
从吉尔吉斯斯坦回来的一年后
we were remodeling this tiny little cabin.
我们重建了这个林中小木屋
And Tommy was using his parent’s old table saw.
Tommy 还用到了他父母的老桌锯
[Dad] Tommy did something that you should never do,
Tommy做的这件事，你永远都不该去做
which is he tried to pull a small piece of wood
他把一小块木头放进锯子里
through the table saw.
据来据去
If the blade catches on the wood,
当锯子刀片碰到木头时
it sucks your hand right back into the blade.
直接就把手指卷进去了
I heard Tommy scream,
我听到Tommy的惨叫
“I fucking cut off my finger, I cut off my finger.”
我切到手指了，我切断手指了
Completely cut his finger off instantly.
瞬间就割断了手指
It was over in the bushes.
手指飞到了草丛
Beth finds the finger laying in this pile of sawdust.
Beth 在锯木屑中找到断指
We throw it on ice, drive to the hospital.
我们用冰裹住，开车去医院
My dad comes in, and he’s like,“You have to fix his finger.”
我老爹进来时，还在念叨，你要把手指带上
[Beth]And so for two weeks, they tried to reattach it.
随后的两周，他们都在设法断指再接
[Tommy]
Three different surgeries.
三位外科大夫
But it became apparent that the finger wasn’t going to survive.
可是，很明显，手指没有能存活下来
This one doctor who was a climber
其中一个大夫自己就是攀岩者
came in and told Tommy that he was going to have to
走进了告诉Tommy说，他需要
come up with a new career now.
从此开始找新的工作
There’s no way he was going to make it as a climber any longer.
他再也不可能回到攀岩这件事
Oh, that was...天呐 ... 这也
either the wrong thing or the right thing to say,
也不知该说是对还是错
because it sure fired him up.
因为这一下子就激怒了Tommy
I was like. ‘Tuck that guy!
我想，见鬼去吧，他
“He doesn’t know what I’m capable of.”
他根本不知道我擅长什么
[Beth] I remember the first time he tried to climb.
我还记得他后来的第一次攀爬
Good, Tommy.
挺棒，Tommy
He was like, “Whoa!”
他，呃， 就像，天呐
You know, it’s going to be hard.
你明白，真的很难
Good job, sweetie.
宝贝，干的好
[Long] When I heard he cut his finger off, I go,
我听到他割断手指后，我就过去了
“Well, so much for Tommy CaIdwell.”
哎，够他受的了。
The grip in climbing is,
攀岩的握力
you wrap your thumb over your finger like that
是需要你用拇指搭在其它手指上，像这样
and pull down on the little edges,
然后去抓住小小的（石头）边缘
and if there’s no finger there, the physics are all wrong.
但如果没有这个指头，物理上的原则都不一样了
I don’t know about that.
我真不知道这个
[Tommy] Everybody around me, except for Beth and my parents,
周围所有的人，除了Beth和我父母
looked at me and they’re like,“He’s done. That’s so sad.”
他们看着我，就像说，他完了，真可悲
I knew it wasn’t going to be easy.
我明白这不容易
But ever since Kyrgyzstan,
但自从吉尔吉斯斯坦事件后
I just have this fire in me
我心里就有一团火
that is different than anything I’ve had before.
和我以前感受的都全然不同
[Dad] He had all these jars of rice and beans and gravel.
他有一堆盛满米粒，豆子或沙砾的瓶子
He’s supposed to jam that nub of a finger in there.
他要把断指的根部扎进瓶子
[Tommy] I just abused the thing
我就是滥用这些东西
to retrain the nerves, to toughen them up.
要重新训练神经，和强壮神经
Those six days of captivity in Kyrgyzstan
在吉尔吉斯斯坦的六天
were so profoundly painful.
痛苦如此深重
At first, I felt overwhelmed
开始时，我感觉到
with fear and fatigue and hunger.
被恐惧、疲劳和饥饿击倒
But at some point, I felt something come over me,
可是，在某一点是，却感觉身体里有某种东西
this reserve of energy,
能量的保存
this confidence.
这一种自信
I knew I was cold, I knew I was hungry,
我明白我很冷，很饿
but those things didn’t matter anymore.
但它们再也不起作用了
I think we all have this idea of where our limits lie.
我认为我们都知道自己的极限在哪里
If you’re hurting really bad,
如果你伤的特别狠
you get to a point where you’re like, “I can’t endure any more.”
你就达到一个点，说，无法忍受更多了。
And it takes something to force you past that.
于是它会推动你穿过去
In Kyrgyzstan, I realized that my preconceived limits
在吉尔吉斯斯坦，我意识到自己曾经预想的极限
were totally off base,
完全不靠谱
that we’re capable of so much more
其实我们可以做到更多
than we really could ever imagine.
比自己想象的多得多
[Beth] There was this really hard climb nobody had done
有些很难的、没有人做到的攀岩
that he tried the year before he cut off his finger,
他手指断以前，很早就尝试过
and he couldn’t do it.
没有成功
A year later, he came back without the finger
一年后，没了手指他再次回来
and he did it.
却成功了
[KeIIy] He cuts off his finger.
他切断了手指
“Oh, no big deal. I’ll just get better after that.”
没啥大事，我会更好的
I have no idea how that’s possible.
真不知道这是怎么做到的
[Dad] That’s when Tommy took his game
这个，是Tommy想要完成他
to the biggest stage on Earth, which is El Cap.
在地球最大舞台上的运动游戏，去攀登El Capitan
[Long]At that time,
那时
there were only a few free climbs that went up El Cap.
登上El Capitan 的徒手抱石攀岩只有几条线路
[John] Some of the hardest big wall climbs ever done.
这些是人们完成过的最难的大岩体攀登
Just to claim one of these routes
即使通过其中一条线路登顶
would have been a monumental achievement
对于世界上最好的攀岩者来说
for the best climbers in the world.
都可以说的不朽功绩
And then Tommy walks into the Valley,
Tommy 于是来到这山谷
missing a finger,
少一根手指
and just started knocking them down, one after the other.
开始要一个一个击败它们
[Long] Over the next five years, he went on a rampage.
此后的五年，他斗志昂扬
[Tommy] I did basically all the existing routes on El Cap.
我完成了现有的全部登顶线路
-Long]Salathe Wall 线路.
-[BethI The Zodiac 线路.
[Dad] El Corazon 线路.
-[Beth] Golden Gate 线路.
-[Dad] The Nose 线路.
[John] Then he starts speed climbing these routes,
然后他开始高速攀登这些线路
linking one into the other.
连接一些线路
[Jason] Two El Cap routes in a day.
有时，一天之间，两次攀爬线路
6,000 feet of climbing.
6000英尺的攀爬
[Long] That was unheard of.
从未有人做到过
-[Beth] You did it! 成功
-[Tommy] Oh, my goodness.天呐
And then I started looking for new routes.
之后就想尝试新的线路
[John] Tommy started looking between the lines
在线路之间，Tommy开始查看
for his own first ascents.
找出他自己的第一条攀登线
[Tommy]  It added that element of the unknown,
就是把未知加入进去
this what-if, like, maybe that could be climbed.
嗯，也许，确实可以攀登
[Long] I think Tommy had become hypnotized
我觉得Tommy是着迷了
trying to figure out, where is the ultimate limit?
想要找出那条终极极线路
[Brettl Oh, shit.哎，糟
[Tommy] I did the first ascent of the Muir Wall.
我先试了Muir Wall 的第一条攀升线
-[Beth] The West Buttress 线路.
-[KeIIy] Dihedral Wall线路.
[Dad]Magic Mushroom.线路
[Long] Anybody that does a first ascent on El Capitan
每一位成功完成El Capitan首次攀爬线路的人
has their place in history forever.
都名垂千古
Tommy did five of them.
Tommy完成了五条线路
[Beth] Anything he could dream up, he did it.
每一个想到的梦想，他都要去实现
And everyone in the climbing world is like, “What the hell?”
在攀岩界大家都感觉是深渊的
[Long]He’s Mr. El Cap.
就是El Cap岩墙
[John] The best big wall climber ever.
是攀岩者可能拥有的最棒大岩墙
[Kelly] And Beth was with him all the time,
Beth一直和他在一起
climbing all of these routes together.
一起攀爬这些线路
[Beth] We just poured our hearts into climbing
我们把心都给予了攀登
and supporting each other on these goals.
彼此支持去完成这些目标
[Long] It was quite a team.
就是像一个团队
[KeIIy] They were known as the first couple of climbing.
他们俩以攀登夫妻档著名
There was one word Beth and Tommy.
就一个字：Beth 和Tommy
[Tommy] We get married.
我们结婚了
We ended up buying property like 20 minutes from El Capitan
我们到离开El Capitan 只有20分钟路程的地方买了地
and building a house there.
建了一所房子
We’re nearly there!
几乎就在那里
[Tommy] We were just going to live in Yosemite
我们要去优胜美地生活
and raise our kids there and keep climbing.
生儿育女，继续攀登
I was good friends with them both
我和他俩都是好友
and we were next-door neighbors.
还是隔壁邻居
They seemed so happy.
看起来他们那么快乐
[Tommy] I’m like, wow, this life
我一直觉得，哇，这才是生活
that I never even saw coming in the first place
我一直都没有想到会发生啥
is starting to just magically appear.
只是等待奇迹自现
Things are going seemingly really well,
看起来事事都好
at least from my mind.
至少我心里是这么觉得的
But I’m noticing, over time, little cracks started to form.
但，随着时间过去，我也注意到一些细小的裂痕
The first inklings of almost hostility towards me.
最初对我的排斥迹象
There was all this weird tension.
有一种奇怪的紧张
And I was just like,
我当时觉得
well, we’ve been together for eight years now.
在一起八年了
Marriages go through troubling times.
婚姻都有艰难时刻
We’ll get through this and just keep climbing.
我们会克服过去，继续攀岩的
[Beth] I think there was a natural growing apart,
我想，这是一种自然而然的分离
desires we had outside of climbing.
攀岩以外的驱动
I think going through a super intense experience
我想通过经历一种超紧张状态
like Kyrgyzstan...
比如像吉尔吉斯斯坦事件
I mean, we were so young.
我意思是，我们都太年轻
Years later, there’s probably a lot that started to come out,
多年以后，也许会发生更多
healing that I hadn’t done.
我无法完成的心理愈合
And at some point, the climbing we had
那时候
wasn’t enough glue to hold it together anymore.
我们一起攀岩的状态也无法弥合彼此
[Kelly] In Kyrgyzstan,
在吉尔吉斯斯坦
Beth was extremely traumatized by those six days,
那六天的经历，对Beth的心理创伤很严重
and Tommy was the person who saved them.
Tommy 救了他们
And so from that, I think
从那个角度，我猜
a sort of dependency probably developed
他们俩之间有可能有一种依赖
that isn’t necessarily the same thing as true love.
并不等同于真爱
[Tommy] Eventually,
最终结果是
she started feeling something for somebody else.
她爱上了别人
And...艾
I don’t know how to summarize this.
不知道该怎么描述总结
This is kind of a hard thing to talk about, but...
谈论这事真是很难，但
that relationship with her and this other man just solidified
她和那个人的关系已经稳定
in a way that she couldn’t walk away from that anymore.
她当时无法一走了之
And she wanted that more than she wanted me.
比起需要我，她那时更需要他
Once the divorce fully happened, I...
等离婚落定
Yeah, I was just crushed.
是呀，当时我是崩溃的
I drove to the rim of Yosemite Valley
我开车到优胜美地的山边
and was looking across at El Capitan.
朝 El Capitan 望着
It felt like El Cap was all I had.
好似 El Capitan 就是我的一切
Early in the morning,
清早
there’s this one panel of the Wall that illuminates first.
岩墙上有一大片岩石会首先闪耀起来
That’s why it’s called the Dawn Wall.
这是人们起名黎明墙的来由
The last unclimbed big swath of stone.
最后一块人们从未攀爬过的大岩体
I had looked at it a little bit before and knew
我看了好一会儿
that it was way too hard, I’d never be able to do it.
知道这条路太难，我可能根本就完成不了
But I was just hurting so bad
但在心灵受伤的那时刻
that I had to figure out a distraction in life.
我必须找到生活的另一面
I couldn’t just sit there and feel the pain.
不能一味坐着，经历悲伤
I decided to go up there alone
我于是决定独自攀登
and beat myself up on the Wall as just a way to cope.
用攀登黎明墙来战胜自我，作为面对生活的方式
I walked around the back to the top of El Cap.
我从山后绕上 El Capitan 山顶
I started rappelling down from above.
把绳索放下去
And I put in a camp so I could stay up there.
架了一顶帐篷，然后可以呆在那儿
And I started going through this process
探索
of searching for a way to climb this section of the Wall.
可以攀爬这一部分大岩体的路
The specific path was totally unknown.
具体的路径全然是未知的
You look for weaknesses in the rock.
在岩石之中找出薄弱点
Corners that you can wedge your body into.
那些可以把身体楔入的石头角落
Cracks for your hands and toes.
可以放住手足的缝隙
Little edges for your fingertips.
手指可以扒住的点滴岩石边缘
Anything that you could possibly grab onto
任何可以抓牢的部位
that would make this wall climbable.
这样才有爬上去的可能
At first, it was just hanging on the rope,
开始时，挂在绳索上
analyzing the surface of the rock
分析岩石表面
to see if there was holds.
查看可以抓住的地方
Just finding something to obsess about
好似拼命找到沉迷的事物
so I wouldn’t obsess about my divorce.
避免落入离婚的困局
[Kelly] I think it’s probably important
我认为这事很重要
that it was an impossible level of rock climbing.
因为这是一种几乎不可能发生的攀岩
When you absorb yourself in some magnificent challenge,
当你沉浸在某种崇高的挑战中
there is no space to be thinking about anything else.
就没有心思去考虑其它了
You know, if you’re heartbroken,
你懂的，在心碎时刻
just throw yourself into an impossible wall.
把自己投身到一堵不可完成的岩墙
[Tommy] So I was sitting up there through this storm.
因此那时，我面临内心的暴风骤雨，枯坐着
My wife has left me.
老婆离开了
She was the only person I had climbed with
她是我攀爬的唯一同行
for, like, ten years.
有十年之久
In my portaledge at night,
那一夜，在悬吊帐篷里
weeping and really feeling sorry for myself,
泪奔，自怨自怜
trying to find this elusive thing
企图找到逃避的路
that probably didn’t even exist.
也许根本就不存在
[Dad] I was concerned.
我关注到
He just seemed to be suffering at that point.
他那时内心受伤很重
And I wanted to see what this was all about,
我也想这是怎么了
so early on in the game I went up there with him.
所以我上去和他一起
[Tommy] I convinced my dad to come up there and belay me,
我说服我老爹上来，帮我放安全绳
so I could start actually trying to climb sections of the route.
这样我就能真正探索攀登的线路
-[Groans] -What the heck?
怎么啦？
[Dad] I really had my doubts as to whether it was going to be
我真是很疑惑
a viable climb.
这是不是可行的攀爬
-[Dad]Be safe. 保持安全
-[Tommy]I will. 会的
-[Dad] Get strong. 挺住
-[Tommy] Yup. 会的
But during that period of time,
就在那段时间
he became convinced that it was somehow possible.
他开始相信，也许是可行的
[Long] Tommy spent an entire year
Tommy花了整整一年功夫
swinging around looking for a route up the Dawn Wall,
晃动在岩石上，寻求黎明墙的登顶途径
trying to connect the dots
尝试把零落的攀爬岩点连接起来
from the bottom all the way to the top
从最底部一直到山顶
so you can someday hope to free climb the whole thing.
梦想有一天，终究可以做到徒手抱石攀登整个黎明墙。
[Tommy]  Eventually, I found a route
最后，我找到了一条路
that seemed like it was theoretically possible,
一条理论上可行的线路
like I found the path through the maze maybe.
好比在迷宫里找到一条出路
But I realized
但我意识到
there was no way I was going to be able to do this alone.
我绝不可能独自一人完成
It’s just a monumental project.
这是一个具有纪念意义的计划
Without Beth, I needed to find a partner,
失去了Beth，我需要找一个同伴
somebody that I could rely on
一个可以信赖
to help me solve this puzzle.
帮助我解决疑惑的同伴
[Wind blowingl
[Tommy] I should wake Kevin up with some coffee.
我要用咖啡叫醒Kevin
Just stretching.
抻一抻
[Tommy] That’s a good idea.
好办法
I felt a little rugged when I first woke up.
我觉得一醒来时有点糟
But how are you feeling?
你感觉如何？
Still stuffy and sore throat. Kind of achy.
有点闷闷的，嗓子疼。别处也疼
[Tommy] I think I got whatever you got.
我觉得和你差不多
[Long] After the first couple of days on the Wall,
在岩壁上的头几天
there’s a small little cadre of people down in the meadow
山下的草坪上聚集了一些人
following their progress.
观望他们的进展
You can get a telescope or a pair of binoculars,
你可以拿一架（天文）望远镜或双筒望远镜
look up at this spectacle happening.
观看这个奇迹
Oh, my God.
老天
-Is he naked or what? 他光着身子吗？
-[Laughing] 哈哈哈
[Tom]My name is Tom Evans. I’ve been
我是Tom Evans
for many years photographing climbers on El Cap.
我已经花好几年拍摄攀登El Cap岩体的人
I usually don’t come in the winter,
一般我不在冬天来
but this is big news in climbing.
在这次是登山界的大新闻
And we’ve all been pulling for him for many years.
我们被他吸引了好多年
[Matt] I was on a little vacation from work,
当时我正在休假中
and I decided to come out from Sacramento
决定从萨克拉门托 （Sacramento） 过来
to watch these guys climb the Dawn Wall.
来观看他们攀登黎明墙
It’s definitely a moment in history.
绝对是历史一刻
To be able to be a part of that and witness it
参与并目睹
is pretty phenomenal.
特别值
[Tommy] Pushing forward.
推进
From here on up, every pitch is pretty legit.
从现在开始，每一绳距都很规范
We’ve got to pace ourselves.
我们需要调整步调
Maybe one or two pitches a day.
大概每天一两个绳距
[Kevin] Come on, Tommy.
加油，Tommy
Good.好
Good, Tommy. Come on.
好哒，Tommy， 加油
[Brett] Nice.
挺棒
[Tommy]Yeah. 是
Come on. 加油
You got it.
成了。
Yeah. Yeah, Kevin.
对对对，Kevin
Nice, dude.
赞一个，哥们
-[Kevin] Cool.
-[Tommy] Dude, that was sick.
哎，糟
It’s day three on the Wall, and we sent pitch 10.
登山第三天。我们到了第十绳距
Yeah! 耶
Yeah. Boom. 耶，好耶
-Things are going good.
进展不错
[Kevin] And the forecast is calling
天气预报说
for super cold windy temps tomorrow,
明天是超级寒冷大风天
so we’re going to rest.
我们准备休整
[Tommy] Urgent weather message.
紧急天气信息
Winds, 50 miles per hour with gusts 75 or higher.
风速，每小时50英里，阵风的时速是75或更高
Impact... downed trees, downed power lines,
影响：倒下的树木，倒下的电力线
flying portaledges.
乱晃的悬空帐篷
[Long] These guys are up there in the middle of winter,
这俩哥们在大冬天里挂在空中
which is almost unheard of.
闻所未闻
But they need it to be as cold as possible
但他们需要寒冷
so they can stick to the tiny holds
因此才能抠进细小的石缝
There’s nobody else on the Wall.
岩壁上没有别的人
Last night, the temperature dropped 30 degrees.
头一个晚上，气温下降了30度
To be up there under these conditions,
在这种情形下呆在岩壁上
it’s horrendous. I don’t know how they do it.
真是可怕。不知道他们是怎样做到的
Carabiners, locked
钩环铁锁，扣好
The windchill’s like negative 20 or something.
寒风指数差不多是零下20度或更低
How you feeling over there, KJ?
Kevin J 你觉得怎样？
It’s getting pretty rowdy.
已经可以用粗暴来形容啦
[Kevin] On El Cap, the wind blows straight up the wall.
在El Cap，风是直接吹到岩壁上去的
The ledge would float up and, bang, back into the wall.
岩石凸都快被吹飞了，砰，风再砸向岩壁
Oh, boy. 哥们，天哪
[Brett] Tommy feels right at home.
Tommy 就像呆在家里一样
Argh![Laughing]
啊哈哈哈
[Tommy] I don’t know what’s wrong with me,
我都不知道我怎么了
but I love this shit.
不过我真喜欢这天气
[Brett] It might be smart to stay in the ledges today.
今天呆在岩架上是很明智的
[Kevin] Because of the windstorm the day before,
因为，前一天的大风暴
all of this moisture froze,
都上冻了
like salt on a Margarita glass on the top of El Cap.
El Cap的岩顶，就像玛格丽塔玻璃杯中的盐
And as soon as the sun hit the top of the Wall,
等太阳光线照到岩峰顶端
that ice just started to shower down on top of us.
冰块就纷至沓来，倾倒到我们头顶
These missiles flying by our camp.
导弹般飞临到我们营地
You hear it before you see it.
还没有看见之前，就能先听到它们
I’m like, this is a deadly situation.
我在想，这也太操蛋了吧
-[Kevin]That was fucked up.
-[Brett]Did you get hit?
简直糟透了 ----- 你被砸到了没？
[Kevin]No, but that was just pure luck.
没，纯粹运气好
[Brett] That was scary.
这真是骇人
[Kevin] I hate that shit.
我恨死这鬼天气了
[Brett]Here come some more big chunks. Tommy forgot his helmet.
大头神经了，Tommy忘记带岩盔
[Kevin] Heads up, Tommy.
看头，Tommy
[Brett]Tommy doesn’t seem too concerned. What the fuck?
Tommy居然不在意。没岩盔又怎么啦
[Kevin] What’s new?
没事吧？
Tommy, he was made for something like this.
Tommy，他就像为此而生
But for me, it took a long time to get comfortable on the Wall.
不过对于我，花了好一段时间才习惯自如
[Long] You can understand, Tommy grew up in the mountains.
你可以理解为，因为Tommy就在山里长大
He’d spent the better part of his adult life
他成年后很大一部分生活
on El Capitan trying to do free climbs.
都是在El Capitan，想要徒手抱石攀爬
But this guy Kevin was raised in Santa Rosa. I think.
但，据我了解，Kevin老弟是在Santa Rosa 长大的
You know, wine country.
你知道吧，就是在葡萄园的地盘上长大的
[kevin] There’s not a lot of rock climbing in Santa Rosa.
Santa Rosa 可是木有多少攀岩的地方
-[Eric]First ascent.第一攀
-[Kevin] Yeah! 耶
[Eric] Don’t fall on the Camaro.
别在Camaro 掉下来喔
[Kevin] I found climbing through the local gym.
我是在当地体育馆里发掘到攀岩的
-[Gail] Bye, honey. Have fun. 儿子再见，好好玩吧
-[Kevin] Bye, Mom. 老妈再见
[Eric] Drive careful.好好开车啦
[Kevin] I got really into this particular form of climbing
我实在是被这种特别的攀岩所吸引
called bouldering.
就是抱石攀岩
It’s typically 30 feet or less.
通常（一个典型的绳距）是30英尺左右
Doesn’t require any gear.
没有其它器械的辅助
Bouldering’s just about athieticism
抱石攀岩具有竞技精神
and difficulty in its purest form.
它纯粹的难度也是魅力
[Long] Bouldering is all about
抱石攀岩
trying the hardest individual moves.
完全是在尝试个人运动中最难的动作
[Groans]
And Kevin quickly became very, very talented.
Kevin很快就证明了自己的天赋
He was one of the best in the world.
他变成世界顶尖之一
But only up to about 30 feet.
但也仅仅，就是上升了30英尺
[Kevin] In 2009, I was at the top of my game in bouldering
2009年，我当时在抱石攀岩的顶峰时期
and looking for something new.
想尝试一点新的
I kept hearing about this futuristic thing
就不断听到这个即将发生的事
that Tommy was working on.
有关Tommy在做的事
I had zero big wall experience.
对于大岩墙攀岩，我是零经验
Tommy and I didn’t know each other at all.
和 Tommy 也根本不认识
But I just sent him a message out of the blue.
莫名其妙地，我就发了一条信息给他
“Hey, do you need a partner?”
嗨，你要不要一个搭档？
And to my utter shock, he said, meet me in Yosemite in October.
出乎我意料，他说，那么，十月我们在优胜美地见面
[Tommy] I knew Kevin by reputation.
我早听说过Kevin
He was this amazingly strong bouldering kid.
他是个特别出色的抱石攀岩小孩
And I thought to myself,“What the heck?
我对自己说，担心啥呢？
“Maybe he could be an asset.”
说不定他正好就是那个真正搭档
Plus, he was the only one interested.
此外，他也是唯一有兴趣的那个
Everybody else thought I was crazy.
其他人都觉得我不可理喻
[Kevin] Show up.
来吧
I remember standing there with Tommy,
我还记得很清楚
who’s a legend figure in my life.
当时和Tommy站一起，他可是我的传奇英雄呢
I feel like such a fucking dork.
我觉得自己特傻
Who am I? I’ve never climbed El Cap.
我是谁呀？从未攀登过El Cap
What a noob.
纯粹一菜鸟
Fiddling around on boulders,
就是在抱石这事上扯蛋
that’s a far cry from being on El Capitan.
和登上El Cap 全不是一回事
[Tommy] First thing I had to do was test him.
我要做的第一件事就是测试
I gave him like an 80 pound haul bag.
我给了他一个80磅的拖袋
[Kevin] A soul crushing load.
真是沉死人的东西
[Tommy] We hiked to the top of El Cap.
我们徒步到达El Cap峰顶
[Kevin]
We spent the night on top.
就在那里露天度过一个晚上
Woke up early the next day...
第二天醒来时
[Tommy] It’s 3:15 in the morning.
是凌晨3:15
Cooking up a little breakfast.
煮了一点早饭
You never get up at 3:00 in the morning to go bouldering.
你永远也不会凌晨3点去抱石攀岩的
[Kevin]...and start rappelling down the face.
然后开始沿绳索下到岩石表层
You start walking backwards.
开始回走
It’s like stepping off the edge of the Earth.
这几乎像从地球的边缘跨出去
You instantly have 3,000 feet of exposure under your butt.
屁股底下，是3000英尺高的野外
[Howling, laughing]
Oh, my God! 天呐
[Tommy] How’s it going up there, Key?
Key，感觉如何？
-[Kevin]Good, I got the bag. 不错，我还有一个包
-[Tommy]And my shoes? 我鞋子在吗？
-[Kevin]And your shoes. 是，还有你鞋子
-[Tommy]Cool, thank you. 酷，谢啦
It’s scary to be a total beginner again.
再次成为新手，这一点挺吓人的
I don’t know any of this stuff.
我对此（这种攀岩）一无所知
Trying to figure out how to jumar a fixed line.
要弄明白怎样用固定绳索上升器
[Groans]
How to set up a portaledge.
如何搭建悬空帐篷
[Clanging]
Sorry, Kevin.抱歉，Kevin
[Kevin] I’ll just hold this quarter in. It’s cool.
我正抓着咱的营帐进来了，超酷
How to take a dump on the side of the Wall.
怎样在岩壁上扔垃圾
-[Tommy] They get every moment. 他们一直在拍摄你呢
-[Josh] Close up. 别说了
[Kevin]At this point, I have no idea what I’m getting into,
直到那会儿，我还是对参与的这件事比较无知
no idea that it’s about to consume six years of my life.
不知道会消耗我六年的时间
[Kelly] When Kevin joined on with Tommy,
当Kevin加入到Tommy一起
it was the first time since getting divorced
这是Tommy离婚后的第一次
that Tommy had a partner.
有了搭档
There’s two bolts and then an old bolt.
有两个螺栓，还有一个旧螺栓
[Kevin]I didn’t know what we were up against,
我并不知道我们面临的是什么
but I was going on faith that this is Tommy’s world.
但我相信这是Tommy的世界
He’s got the clear vision of what this could be.
他对所作所为一清二楚
And I’m just going to trust that.
我只需要信任它就好
[Tommy] The basic strategy early on
最开始的计划
was not to climb the route from the bottom.
并不是从岩底攀登
It was to identify the hardest sections
无疑这是最难的部分
and focus on those first.
把注意力集中在这里
[Kevin]There were all these question marks.
所有的问号都在这儿
Come on, Tommy. 加油，Tommy
[Tommy] OK, take it there. 好吧，拿上去
Oh, I got the pinch with my right hand instead of my left.
我用右手标记了，没有用左手
[Kevin] Working it out. 完成它
Constantly working it out.不断完成
Early on, most of it was figuring out what didn’t work.
起先，大部分计划都是在琢磨难以完成的部分
Right in the middle of the Wall,
在岩壁的中部
we were gonna have to traverse it sideways.
我们必须窄道横穿
Come on.加油
I don’t see any holds,
我简直什么抓缝也看不到
but I try to harness some of Tommy’s optimism.
不过我控制自己学习Tommy的乐观
[Tommy] After the traverse,
在横穿以后
there’s this 8 and 112 foot blank section.
紧接著就是8到112英寸的空白地带
Completely smooth.
完全是光溜溜的岩壁
Nothing that you could even get your fingernails behind.
没有任何可以手指触碰的地方
The only way was to just leap.
唯一的办法就是跳跃
This crazy dynamic move.
真是疯狂的动作
The Dyno.在Dyno段
I didn’t really believe it would be possible
我真不敢相信这怎么可能呢
until I saw Kevin try it.
直到看见Kevin在尝试
Yeah, man. It was close.
兄弟，接近了
He showed me that it was.
他展示给我
[Kevin] Come on. All you got.
加油，快了
Above the Dyno, you have pitch after pitch
Dyno段之上，每一个绳距
of have super smooth granite,
都是光滑无比的花岗岩
extremely polished.
呈极端抛光状
Because of Tommy’s missing index finger,
因为Tommy没有了食指
he’s using his thumbs in crazy ways.
他很不可思议地用拇指替代
Shit.狗屎
Argh! 啊
Holy crap, that is hard.
艾玛，真是太难了
13B.
13C. 14A.
[Long] To understand the difficulty of this route,
想要理解这段路径的困难度
you have to understand climbing grades.
你不得不要先理解攀岩等级
Climbers use a numerical system
攀岩者是使用一套数值系统
to rate the difficulty of each pitch.
来评估每一个绳距的难度系数
The higher the number, the harder the pitch.
系数越高，绳距难度越大
Once you get into 513 and 514 level,
一旦到达513和514的难度系数
that’s virtuoso territory.
那是大师级的恐怖系数了
The Dawn Wall has more hard pitches
黎明墙的绳距难度系数
than every other route on El Cap combined.
比所有El Cap岩墙的难度系数都要更高
I always thought it was futile
我总是认为
in terms of doing the whole thing.
要完成整个攀登几乎是徒劳
This is a pipe dream, man. Come on.
哥们，这是梦想啊，加油
[Kevin] The next few years were a grind.
此后的几年真是很磨人
Coming back every spring and every fall for months at a time.
每个春秋时季，都会回来呆上几个月
-[Tommy] Come on. 加油
-[Thunderclap]
[Kevin] Living on the Wall takes a huge toll.
住了岩壁上是要付出代价的
[Tommy] This is what El Cap does to your feet.
这是 El Cap 对你脚丫子的所作所为
[Kevin] We’d stay up there a few days...
我们要呆好几天.......
[Brett] Oh, my God. That’s a lot of air time.
天呐，真是飞天了
[Kevin]...go down, rest,
下来，休息
try again.
再尝试
There were always new problems to face.
不断有新问题出现
[Tommy] Get out of here!
快撤出来
Come on, Kevin. Do it, man.
加油，Kevin，你行的，兄弟
-Really close. 几乎抓到了
-Oh, I sprained my ankle. 我伤到了脚踝
-Are you OK, man? 怎么样，兄弟
-Oh, shit. 糟透了
[Kevin]So many reasons to give up.
N多可以放弃的理由
[Brett] Oh, shit. 啊，糟了
[Tommy] Man, I think I have broke or dislocated ribs.
兄弟，我觉得我胸骨折断了，要不就是错位了。
We’re heading to the clinic.
我们跑医疗室
Maybe they’ll just pop it back in.
也许他们可以设法弄好
[Kevin]They will, and we’ll go back up later tonight.
他们会，哎，我们会晚上再过来
But Tommy was committed.
但是，Tommy决意已定
[Tommy] Come on, Kevin! Come on!
加油，Kevin，加油
[Kevin]There were times I thought he was totally crazy.
我不由自主有时想，他真是疯了
Come on! 加油
Yee-hoo! 呼呼
Whoo! Ow-ow! 哇塞
[Kevin]When we weren’t together on the Wall,
当我们不在岩墙时
we would go home to our own worlds,
我们就回到自己的世界
check in on loved ones.
和亲爱的家人照个面
It’s gross. I can see the oil on your hair.
油腻腻的，我都看见你头发上的油了
OK, I’m just totally being a mom.
好吧，我就是个老妈的命
[kevin]
Try to get some good rest
要好好休息哦
and find motivation for the next round of attempts.
充电了才好继续尝试
[Tommy] When I wasn’t on the Dawn Wall,
我不在黎明墙时
I was living by myself in Colorado,
我就独自住在科罗拉多州
training and obsessing.
一边训练，一边沉迷
I was really lonely, honestly.
实话实说，很孤独
I met this girl named Becca.
后来遇到了Becca
[Becca]We started dating.
我们就开始约会了
He was thoughtful and considerate,
他很体贴周到
but from the beginning, it was pretty obvious
不过从一开始，就挺明显
his mind was completely occupied by the Dawn Wall.
他的全部关注是黎明墙
It wasn’t just a climb.
这不是一次简单的攀爬
It was all consuming.
这是全部的投入
We were trying to build a relationship.
我们准备建立稳定关系
But he would go out to Yosemite for months at a time,
但他需要隔一段时间就去优胜美地
giving everything to the Dawn Wall.
把一切都投入到黎明墙
Long For years, Tommy put his whole life on hold
多年以来，Tommy把他的全部生活都后置了
so he could give every last ounce of his body and soul
这样才能把他所有的心身
to this impossible quest.
都投放进这个不可能的探索中
[Kevin] I could never tell if we were wasting our time
我永远也不知道，到底我们是在浪费时间呢
or we were in pursuit of something grand.
还是我们在追求某些崇高的目的
Come on! 加油
[Becca] I’d go out to Yosemite
我也来到优胜美地
and I’d watch him from the meadow.
从草地上举头看他
It looked completely ridiculous.
看起来太荒谬了
Ah, shoot. 嚓
I think we all admire people who are dedicated.
我想我们都对奉献者赞美有加
But at some point, you start to wonder,
但，有时，你会想
where are the lines between dedication and obsession?
奉献和沉迷，之间的界限到底是什么？
[Dad] He was going through emotional agony.
他正在经历情感上的苦难
This climb has been gut wrenching.
攀爬是痛苦的
I want this for him so badly.
我是如此之渴望
[Tommy] Argh! 啊
-[Mom] Oh, he fell off. 吖，掉下来了
-Oh.
[Kelly] Man. I mean, you’ve failed on this thing 800 times.
兄弟，我说，你已经失败800次了
How can you continue to beat your head against this wall?
怎么才能继续头顶着墙攀岩下去呀？
[Kevin]After years of effort,
经年的努力
it didn’t feel like we were any closer to our dream.
我们甚至都没有更接近梦想一点点
[Becca] He’s worked so hard.
他是这么用心
Why am I crying right now?
我怎么就哭了呢？
This project! Argh!
这个计划，啊
[Dad] This makes me wonder
我想到
if he bit off more than he could chew.
如果他能咬牙顶住，而不是咽下
Oh, it’s so good to have you down.
哎，你能下来真是太棒了
[Tommy] After all this failure, I started to wonder
重重失败以后我开始想
if maybe this climb really was impossible.
这个攀岩真是不可行
Maybe I wasn’t good enough.
也许我还不够厉害
-[Kevin] Morning. 早上好
-[Tommy] Morning. 早上好
[Tom]Tommy and Kevin have been up there, this is their 8th day.
Tommy和Kevin，已经在岩墙上，是第八天了
They’re halfway up the Wall.
他们已经半墙高
They got past 70 mile an hour winds, the ice falls.
他们经历了时速70英里的风暴，落冰
They climbed a lot of difficult rock.
他们爬过许多困难的大石
Now they’ve got today a very hard section to do.
此刻，他们今天要做一件巨难的事
They’re here. They’ve got to go across this traverse.
在这儿，他们要横着穿越窄道
140, I think it is.
我觉得有140 尺
If they can get that done, they’re well on their way.
一旦穿越过去，后面就好办了
[Long] The hardest individual part of this 3,000 foot puzzle
3000英尺迷局之中，最难的个体部分
is the traverse.
就是横道穿越
The bottom section of the route
线路的底部
follows a vague series of cracks and corners in the rock.
紧接着一系列的岩石缝隙和戳出来的石块
But after 1,000 feet, those cracks and corners dead end.
但1000英尺以后，这些缝隙和石头戳角就隐没了
300 feet to the left, there’s another series of features
左侧的300英尺，才有一串石缝
that angles up to the top.
曲折上升
The trick is,
问题是
how do you traverse this 300 foot blank section
怎么才能通过这300英尺的空白墙面
right in the middle of the Wall?
正正在岩墙中央？
[Kevin] There’s this band of rock
这一岩块
that’s a slightly different color and texture.
从颜色和质地，都有点不一样
[Long] Everything above and below it
之上和之下
is impossible to free climb.
完全无法抱石攀爬
But the composition of that band
可是，就是这一块构造
is such that it has a few holds on it.
结构如此这番，几乎无手可下
[Kevin] Over the last six years, we spent over 100 days
过去的六年里，我们花了一百多天
trying to get across this traverse.
企图横穿窄道
[Tommy] Thousands of tries on that single pitch.
就在这单一的绳距，已经尝试了数千遍
I’ve never done it.
我从未成功
[Kevin] Now we have to do it for the very first time...
现在，我们要第一次跨越
[Tom] Looks like Tommy’s getting ready.
Tommy 看起来准备好了
[Kevin]...in the moment, on the push.
这一刻，出发
Go get it.
祝成功
[Tommyl It’s really unnerving.
充满紧张的时刻
You’re just waiting to slip off at any moment.
任何时间都可能掉下、滑下
[KeIIy] It’s kind of funny.
有点荒唐可笑
This 3,000 foot wall, and it’s coming down to millimeters
3千英尺高的岩墙，只有几毫米的地方
of skin contact on your fingertips.
给指尖的一点点皮肤可以接触
It becomes such a zoomed-in world.
它几乎就像到了微观世界
[Kevin] There’s one way to get across,
只有一条路可以通过
and it is made up of all these little sequences
由最小的单位组成
that have to be done perfectly.
只有完美无误的动作才能完成
You miss a hold, it’s impossible.
失去一个握抓，就前功尽弃
[Tommyl Yeah, dude. 是呀，哥们
[Kevin] You grab it wrong, it’s impossible.
抓错地方，也一样前功尽弃
[Tommy] Nice. 好
[Kevin] We’re trading attempts.
我们正在尝试
Tommy ties in and just flips that switch.
Tommy 试了进去，接触开始点
Alright. Go get it, Tommy.
不错，继续，Tommy
[Tommy] You grab these sharp holds,
抓到这锋利的握抓点
like razor blades.
就像抓在刀片上
[Kevin] Come on! 加油
[Tommy] Span as far as you can.
尽可能展开身体
[Kevin] Come on!加油哦
[Tommy] So stretched out.
如此之展开
I suddenly felt this confidence.
突然我就感到了自信
I knew exactly how each finger was going onto each hold,
知道每一节手指怎么做到彼此相握
where the little ripples on the rock were digging into my shoes.
岩石上的碎屑渗透进鞋子里
After years of working on that pitch,
只要你在这样绳距上多年努力
it just came together in this amazing, magical way.
它就会以惊人又神奇的方式组合起来
[Kevin] Yes, come on!
赞，加油
Come on! 加油
Whoa! 哇
[Crowd] Whoo! 呼呼
Ow—ow—ow—ow!
[Long] When I heard that Tommy had done pitch 15,
我听到Tommy完成15绳距时
that was like,“You’ve got to be kidding me!”
几乎以为：这不是开玩笑吧
For the first time,
第一次
these guys actually have a shot at maybe doing this thing.
他们俩激起可以完成攀登的希望
[Kevin] When Tommy got across,
当Tommy完成穿越
it was a big moment.
真是伟大一刻呀
Everything was rolling, and now it was my turn.
都可以翻页的，此刻我要去尝试
Over the years, we realized
过去很多年间，我们都认识到
sometimes the best conditions are at night.
最佳的攀岩点是夜间
It’s colder. It’s drier.
既寒冷、又干燥
So there’s better friction on the rock.
因此岩石的缝隙更合适（抓握）
At first, it’s scary.
开始时，这挺吓人的
But after a while, you forget how high off the ground you are
但过一会儿，就会忘记你距离地面的高度
and you can focus just on the climbing.
于是就能专注在攀爬上
[Groaning]
Tried it a few times.
试过几次
I wasn’t that close.
无法靠近
We rappelled back to our camp below the traverse.
我们放绳回到窄道之下的大本营
I was stoked for Tommy, a little stressed for myself.
我给Tommy做了吃的，自己则挺紧张
[Long] So Tommy’s made it through the traverse.
这样Tommy就完成了横穿窄道
He still has to get past the Dyno
他还有 the Dyno 这个绳距要完成
and the Long Run to Wino Tower.
还有从the Long Run 到 Wino Tower 的绳距
But first, he has to wait for Kevin to catch up.
但首先，他要等Kevin 赶上来
[Phone rings]
[Tommy] Hello? 喂
[Branch]‘Hey, guys. This is John Branch from the NY Times.
嗨，哥们，我是《纽约时报》的John Branch
-‘How’s it going up there?’ 你们怎样？
-Tommy]Good, John. 挺好，John
[Branch]‘Tommy, I know that you made it to 15 last night.
Tommy，知道你昨晚完成了15绳距
‘It’s very exciting,
真令人激动兴奋
‘so I appreciate you guys taking just a few minutes to talk.’
所以感谢，要花你们几分钟时间来聊一聊
We’re always looking for stories that are a little bit
我们一直在寻找一些故事
out of the mainstream sports realm.
不完全是在主流的体育范畴
Every time we start a hard pitch...
每次开始尝试比较难的绳距
[Branch]I knew about the Dawn Wall and Tommy Caidwell’s quest.
我知道黎明墙，也知道Tommy Caidwell 的追求
And when I heard that Tommy did pitch 15, I thought,
听到Tommy完成15绳距的消息，
if it was ever going to happen, this might be the time.
我想： 如果这件事要发生，那，现在就是它了
We recognized
我们意识到
this is not only the best climbing story of the year,
它不仅仅是当年最佳攀岩
but maybe of our generation.
甚至可能是我们这一代里的最佳攀岩
‘We talked about follow-up stories.’
我们讨论了后续报道
Quickly typed up a story.
很快写出报道
The next day, it ran in the paper.
第二天，就上了新闻
[Kevin] It was on the front page of The New York Times,
《纽约时报》头版报道
and it just exploded.
它成了爆炸性新闻
[Branch] It was the most viewed story at nytimes.com.
也成为 nytimes.com 网站点击率最高的新闻
Tons of comments. Lots of questions.
雪花般的评论，无穷多的问题
People care about this.
人们关注它
[Long] When John Branch,
John Branch 是
the Pulitzer Prize winning journalist, got a hold of it,
普利策获奖记者，当他抓到这个报道时，
it just got its own momentum.
正好抓到了一个最佳点
And it just got bigger and bigger from there.
此后影响越来越大
[Kevin] There was follow-up stories
很多后续报道
and a flood of media requests
潮水一般的媒体
from every major news outlet in the world.
从世界各大新闻机构报道出来
[Presenter] Picture this. Our next guests talk to us
想象一下，我们下一位要对话的嘉宾
as they were suspended high up in mid air.
此刻正悬挂在半空
[Tommy]‘We’re sitting in a portaledge, which is basically’
我们正坐在悬挂帐篷里
a hanging cot with an aluminum frame.
悬挂帐篷就是有铝制框架的悬挂小床
[Presenter] That’s professional climber Tommy CaIdwell
这位专业攀岩家Tommy Caldwell
ten days into what’s considered
有十天之久
one of the world’s most daunting climbing challenges.
正在进行被世人认为是世上最令人敬畏之攀岩
This is crazy.
疯啦
[Presenter] ‘Best of luck.’祝好运
Great. Thank you so much.
好的，谢谢。
Guess we hang up. I don’t really know.
挂了。其实我不知道
They don’t tell us what to do when it’s over.
他们并没有告诉我们何时结束
[Car horn blares]
[Woman] Oh, my God! 天哪
How many days does it take?
要多久？
[Tommy] All of a sudden,
突然之间
there are crowds of people congregating in the Valley.
大批人群在山谷里开始聚集起来
Let’s turn now to this historic feat by two American climbers.
让我们转向创造美国攀岩历史的两位
Perched on a cliff above Yosemite.
栖留在优胜美地的悬崖上
The famously steep face of El Capitan.
El Capitan 岩墙上最著名的陡峻之地
The whole media thing was very strange for me.
对我来说，完全不了解媒体
[Presenter]
The climb of the century.
世纪性攀岩
it's just been extraordinary
了不起
A real cliffhanger. Did I just say that?
我是不是该这么说： 真正的悬崖高手
They were just saying these ludicrous things.
他们用尽赞美的语言
-Two American hikers. 两位美国户外远足
-Daredevils. 胆大冒险者
-Thrill seekers. 激动人心的探索者
-Adrenaline junkies. 肾上腺飙高的冒险家
Scaling the cliff known as El Capitan.
一步步在攀爬 El Capitan 悬崖
[Tommy] That’s not even El Cap.
这太不像 El Cap了
Inching up without any climbing tools.
没有任何登山器械，一寸寸的徒手攀岩
I’m wearing pretty much the same gear as the guys up in Yosemite.
我现在的装备，和优胜美地的那两位几乎一样
I like the second picture, so we’ll hover here.
我喜欢第二张图，让我们从这里开始
[Tommy] The Dawn Wall was always this personal journey.
黎明墙本是一趟个人之行
[Presenter]This was a bad idea.
这想法不成吧
And obviously,
显而易见
this turned into something very different from that.
这变得完全不是一回事了
So don’t understand how they could possibly do it.
完全不懂他们是怎么做到的
I hope they make it, but I don’t understand it.
希望他们成功，不过我还是不能理解
It’s the challenge.
这是挑战
Yeah, the challenge of it. No. thanks.
是，挑战。不，谢谢（我不会去挑战）
[Tommy]Suddenly, the whole world was watching this climb.
突然之间，整个世界都像是在观看攀岩
[Kevin] Which wasn’t the best timing for me personally,
个人而言，不是最佳时机
because I still had to do pitch 15.
因为我还需要完成15绳距
[Long]  At this point,they’ve established a base camp
此时，他们已经建立了一个大本营
a couple of hundred feet below the traverse.
在窄道下面一两百英尺的地方
So when Kevin’s ready to climb,
所以，Kevin 准备攀爬时
they go up the fixed ropes to the start of pitch 15.
他们就沿着绳索上升到15绳距的起点
Tommy sets up his belay,
Tommy 帮他准备好栓绳
and Kevin tries to get across this thing.
Kevin 就准备窄道横穿
Here would be actually a big moment on the climb.
这将是攀岩的一个大时刻
Drove all the way out here today just to see this.
今天一路开车过来，就是想目睹这过程
[Kevin] It was important to get through pitch 15
穿越15绳距很重要啦
and catch up to Tommy’s high point
这样可以追上Tommy 的最高攀爬点
as soon as possible.
尽可能地
Come on, Key. You got it.
加油，Kevin，你可以的
Oh!
[Kevin] Every fall, you go back to the start of the pitch,
每次摔落，都必须回到那个绳距的起点
rest for at least an hour...
休息至少一个小时
...try again.
然后继续
Every attempt, you wear off more skin.
每次尝试，皮肤就被擦掉一些
You run out of a little more energy.
精力也被慢慢耗掉
[Reporter 1] Everything was going smoothly
诸事顺利
until Jorgeson couldn’t grasp pitch 15.
直到 Kevin Jorgeson 无法完成15绳距为止
[Reporter 2] Stopped by the sheer difficulty of the climb.
被攀岩的纯难击倒
[Reporter 3] As the razor-sharp hand holds
当刀锋般的岩石
tore the skin off his fingertips.
刮去他指尖的皮肤
[Kevin] So everyone’s tuning in
当大家都关注到
in the middle of guys living on the side of the Wall...
在岩壁上呆着的两哥们
[Reporter 4] History is on hold in Yosemite National Park.
优胜美地国家公园正在创造历史
[Kevin] ...and one of them’s stuck.
有一个人搞砸了
Argh!
[Reporter 5]
Kevin Jorgeson is stuck.
Kevin Jorgeson 卡壳了。
-[Tommy] That was close, dude. 快了，兄弟
-[Kevin] I know. 我知道
[Tommy] You just started to fall apart a little bit there.
你离开那儿很近才掉下来的
[Branch] It’s a pretty fascinating drama
这超级戏剧化
unfolding in real time, literally in front of our eyes.
真实时间就这样展开，简直可以说，就在我们眼前
People who I’m sure had no idea what a pitch was
对绳距毫无概念的人们
were now going, “Pitch 15! Come on, Kevin! You can do it!”
现在也念叨着：15绳距，加油，Kevin，你能做到的
[Groans]
You’ll get it, dude. That was really close.
你绝对可以的，已经挺近了
[Tommy] I spent a few days not climbing,
好几天我都没有攀爬
just belaying Kevin over and over again on pitch 15.
在15绳距那里，一次次帮助Kevin准备栓绳，
[Groans]
It was harder than any pitch of climbing he’d ever done.
这比他经历过的所以绳距都要更难
[Kevin] Fucker! 见鬼
[Tommy] He just kept falling and falling.
他不停掉下来
I had honestly started to lose hope that he was going to do it.
我真心失去信心，疑惑他能不能完成
[Kevin] Last night was my third day
昨天已经是尝试的第三天
of battle with pitch 15.
这场与15绳距的争斗
Still didn’t do it.
我还是败了
After trying so many times, I’ve destroyed my fingers.
试过那么多次以后，手指都磨损了
So I decided to take a rest day and let my fingers heal.
因此我决定休整一天，恢复手指
[Long] Meanwhile, Tommy hasn’t climbed for days.
与此同时，Tommy 停止攀岩已经好多天
And he has to be thinking,
他在想
I can’t stay up here indefinitely waiting for Kevin.
我不能停在这儿，遥遥无期地等待Kevin
I mean, there’s very few people in the world
我意思是，世上很少有人
that have ever even spent that much time on a wall.
在一面岩墙上花这么长时间
[Tommy] Living on the Wall just wears you down.
住在岩墙上真的很消磨斗志
It’s just harsh up there.
就是很严酷的啦
You can’t even walk.
你都没法走一走
You’re not sleeping great at night.
夜里也睡不好
You’re not eating normal foods, drinking enough water.
吃不上正常食品，喝水不够
It’s hard to climb your best under those conditions.
这种条件下，很难发挥攀岩最佳水平
[Branch] Every day that goes by, maybe Tommy suddenly gets sick.
也许哪一天，Tommy 突然生了病
Maybe the weather changes.
也许天气突变
[Tommy] I felt like I had to continue.
我觉得我应该继续前进
[Long] So they devised a plan.
所以他们重新设置了一个计划
Tommy’s going to press on and try the Dyno pitch,
Tommy 往下一个绳距 （the Dyno 绳距）进发
hoping that Kevin eventually will get across 15
同时期待Kevin 最终克服15绳距
and he can catch up.
然后他可以追赶上来
[Kevin]That night, we go up our fixed lines
那天夜里，我们出发到已经固定的线路
and I belay Tommy on pitch 16, the Dyno pitch.
我帮Tommy准备16绳距，the Dyno 绳距
[Tommy] I had tried the Dyno move
我曾经试过在 Dyno 绳距那里移动
hundreds of times over the years.
过去几年间，有上百次吧
Never done it.
从未成功过
I’d rebuilt it on the shed at my home,
我在自己家里重建了一个木棚
so I could just practice this one stupid move.
为了我能够练习这个蠢笨的动作
Just before we went for our final push
直到出发去最终的攀岩时刻
I was completely frustrated,
整个人都不好了，崩溃
staring at these photos of the Wall.
盯着岩墙的这些图片
I started to notice cracks and edges that go down and around.
我开始关注上下左右的细缝和突角
So I came up with this idea
于是有了一个想法
to do the most ridiculous pitch of climbing.
来完成这个最荒谬的攀爬
[Kevin] His idea was to just climb in a giant circle
他想的是，用大回环的方式爬上去
around the Dyno. I was like, “Really?”
就是在Dyno绳距那里。我表示说：真的？
[Brett] So to get around about eight feet...?
就为了这八英尺？
[Tommy] Yeah, climb like 200.
是呀，要爬200
Tommy’s currently working out the world’s hardest down climb.
Tommy正在做的是，世上最艰难的下岩
We do hard moves going straight up, hard moves going sideways.
我们一般是攀上，更难的是水平移动
I should add a down climb.
我要加上一个下移攀爬动作
That way, we just get the full package.
这样，我们把攀岩的动作就弄完整了
Down climbing, it’s so unnatural.
下岩攀爬，是如此不自然
[Tommyl Falling. 跌
[Kevin] It’s like running backwards.
这就像往后跑
[Tommy] That felt horrible.
恐怖
[Kevin] Good, Tommy.
不错，Tommy
Nice. 挺棒
Come on. Focus.
加油，集中注意力
Good. 赞
[KeIIy] This loop pitch,
这个回环绳距
it’s like walking around the block to cross the street.
就好比兜了一圈穿过街道
It is just a little bit ridiculous.
看起来挺荒唐
But it’s also kind of brilliant.
但真的是才华横溢
[Kevin] Come on. 加油
Come on. 加油啦
[KeIIy] This thing that had been shutting him down
阻碍他的这个东西
for all these years,
阻碍了这么多年
and then he just looks at it with a new set of eyes
然后现在他用一个新的视角去看它
and finds a new solution.
就找到了新的解决方案
[Tommy] Yeah. 耶
The Dyno!
Whoo! 呜哈哈
[Tommy] How is the skin, dude?
兄弟，皮肤好些没？
It’s not healing very quickly,
恢复不快
which is frustrating.
这一点最令人沮丧
[Long] While Kevin’s waiting for his fingers to heal,
当Kevin等着他手指复原时
Tommy continued pushing the route higher and higher.
Tommy 已经把绳距往上推的越来越高
What you do every day is,
你每天要做的是
you get to a high point, and then you leave fixed ropes
上到一个更高的绳距，把绳索固定住
that go back down to the camp.
然后下到大本营
The next day, you motor back up the ropes to the high point
第二天，开动，把绳索推向另一个高绳距
and then carry on.
这样不断前行
So, even though they might be working
因此，尽管他们俩
on different parts of the Wall,
在岩墙的不同部位忙乎
they’re doing it together. Kevin belays Tommy,
他们其实是一起搭档的。Kevin 给Tommy 放绳索
and once Tommy’s done, they both go back down to the camp.
等Tommy完成后，他们俩一起下回到大本营
[Kevin] Tommy’s just forging on.
Tommy 不断推进着
Every pitch gets him further away from where I’m stuck.
每一个绳距的前推，都把我卡壳的地方甩的越来越远
[Tommyl One more down.
接着下去吧
[Kevin]There’s so much distance between our high points
我们之间的最高绳距，彼此距离越来越远
that I’m not going to be able to close that gap
我没有可能把这个差距填补上了
in a reasonable amount of time
在可能的合理时间内
unless I do this.
除非我已经做到（完成15绳距）
[Tommy] Every time I would look over in his portaledge
每次我看到他在悬空帐篷里
he would just be following news updates,
他在看新闻更新
staring at his fingertips,
一边看他的手指尖
mumbling to himself.
一边叨叨着什么
[Kevin] Trying to convince myself these actually look good.
试着说服自己这还是挺好的
Tommy, do you have the Ibuprofen?
Tommy，你有没有布洛芬？
Oh, yeah. 有
[Kevin] After two days resting, I felt resolved.
又休息两天后，我觉得需要有一个了结
This was the day it had to happen.
该发生的就是该让它发生
It’s still pretty warm out.
天气还比较暖和
And so I’m going to wait a few more hours
所以要再等几个钟点
for the temperatures to drop even more
等温度降下去
to give myself every bit of friction you can.
给自己尽可能的摩擦力
[Tommy] You ready? 准备好了没？
[Kevin] Ready as I’m ever going to be.
像以前一样，准备好了
I’ve been waiting for days for the skin to heal,
我已经等了多天，等皮肤愈合
for this moment to come.
等着这一刻来到
There’s a nice cold breeze blowing up the wall.
凉风轻吹着岩壁
I felt weightless.
我觉得自己身轻如燕
I was just floating across the pitch.
我几乎要漂浮过这个绳距
[Tommy] Hold it together.
抓牢
[Groans]
Come on, Kevin. Do it, man.
加油，Kevin，兄弟，做吧
You got it.
你可以的
Come on. 加油
You got it. 快了
Come on. Find it.
加油，找到那个点
Good. Come on.
不错。加油啦
Argh!
[Tommy] Oh, that was so good, dude.
兄弟，还是挺棒的了
[Kevin] Everything was perfect, and I still didn’t do it.
万事俱备，结果我还是失败了
[Matt] Come on, Kevin.
加油，Kevin
[Kevin] I tried four times that night.
那个晚上我试了四次
Fucker! 鬼
[Man] He’s off.
又摔下来了
[Kevin] I just kept falling.
我不断掉下来
Shit! 狗屎
Tonight... 今晚
...didn’t go so well.
真不顺
It was a battle, and I didn’t win.
这是战斗，我就是没有赢下来
It was pretty clear that that was it.
它就像
Like, you had your chance.
比如，你是有机遇的
You weren’t good enough.
但你还不够好
Yeah, it’s pretty fucked.
是呀，真是糟透了。
Now you’re the guy that almost climbed the Dawn Wall.
此刻你几乎就是要成功登上黎明墙的人了
So how much did you enjoy that process?
完成这过程的满足度有多少？
Because that’s all you get.
因为这是你应得的
[Branch] Editors and I started talking.
我和编辑们讨论
Is it now time to do a story about what happens
是不是该写出这个故事
if he doesn’t make it?
但他并没有完成
We all want happy endings, but as a journalist, you’re like
我们都喜欢大团圆结局，可是，作为记者
“That’s an incredible story.”
你应该明白，不可思议的故事是什么
What’s the ethos in climbing?
攀登的精神是什么？
Do you say, you go ahead without me?
你想问，就这样你自己前进了
Do you leave a guy behind?
把同伴拉着后面
Are they having this conversation
他们是否在黑夜中的悬空帐篷里
in the portaledge at night?
聊过这些？
[RainfaII]
This would be nice to check the radar.
查看雷达可能会有用些
[kevin] The next day, the weather was starting to get bad.
第二天，天气更糟
And I knew what I needed to do.
我知道我需要做什么
[Tommy] 20%.
[Kevin] Today? 今天吗？
[Tommy] Next like four days.
之后还要有四天
I’m just going to throw in the towel
我准备撑到 the Towel
and support Tommy to the top.
支持Tommy 一直到成功登顶
[Long] From here on out,
从这时候开始
Kevin’s just going to belay Tommy
Kevin一心帮助Tommy放绳索
and follow him up the ropes.
跟他上绳索
So they go up to Tommy’s high point,
所以他们一点点把Tommy 的最高绳距提升
where he starts up the last hard pitches
直到他通过那几个最艰难的绳距
of the long run to Wino Tower.
达到Wino Tower
[Kevin] There I was, watching Tommy
我就在那儿，看着Tommy
climb with so much confidence
充满信心地攀爬
toward the completion of this dream.
攀上他的梦圆点
Even if I can’t do this, I was really happy for Tommy.
即使我自己没有成功，我还是为此替Tommy感到快乐
What a special moment
一个特别的时刻
to witness this piece of history.
亲眼目睹这一节历史
And I was there to help Tommy realize this vision.
我参与去帮助Tommy实现了梦想
After everything he went through,
他经过的每一步
so much struggle,
这么多的挣扎
the injuries, the doubts.
伤痛、疑惑
For Tommy it was like, this is it.
对于Tommy，就这样了
Come on, Tommy.
加油，Tommy
[Tommy] Boom! 碰
[Crowd cheers]
Woo-hoo! Feels good.
呼哈哈，感觉良好
[Long] I’m down in the meadow
我在草坪上
watching Tommy trying to get to Wino Tower,
看着Tommy即将到达 Wino Tower
which is the next big feature above them.
是等待他们的一个大界标
It’s this mythical landmark
它是神奇的地标
about two-thirds of the way up El Capitan.
El Capitan 三分之二的分界
[Kelly] This three foot pedestal 2,000 feet up the Wall.
这个三英尺的石头台基，位于岩墙的2000 英尺高的地点
[Long] The first horizontal ledge
是整座岩墙上的第一块水平突角
where you can stand up, sit down, lie down
可以让你站立，坐下，躺下
on the entire route.
在整个线路上
[Kelly] And it signifies the end of the hardest climbing.
它意味着艰苦攀岩过程的结束
[Tommy] One more hard pitch to get to Wino Tower.
到达Wino Tower之前，还有一个苦逼绳距
That’s crazy!
真是疯狂啊
For years, I’d envisioned this moment of getting to Wino Tower.
好多年来，我都在臆想登上Wino Tower那一刻
So I’m freaking out inside.
内心深处都沸腾了
[Kevin] Good, Tommy. Come on.
赞，Tommy，加油
[Tommy] Climbing really tense and kind of shaking nervous.
爬的紧张，神经都颤抖了
[Kevin] Keep breathing, dude.
保持呼吸，哥们
Come on. 再加油
Good. 好
[Tommy] Just trying to calm myself down enough
需要自我镇定住
to make it through the final last little bit.
直到通过最后那几块
[Kevin] Yeah! 耶
[Howls] Ow! 嗷
[Sighsl
[Laughs]
[Tommy] Oh! I feel a little shaky.
觉得自己都发抖了
Yeah, I might pass out.
是，快昏过去了
I can’t believe I’m here right now.
真不敢相信我已经在这儿了
I know it’s not over yet, but that’s big.
虽然知道还不是最后终点，但这是一大步
I’m at Wino Tower.
我在 Wino Tower
[Brett] What are you feeling?
感觉如何？
I want Kevin to experience this, too. for sure.
毫无疑问，我希望Kevin也能经历这个
[Tommy] It was this huge victory.
这是巨大的胜利
But it’s totally trumped by the fact
但却被一个事实压倒
that Kevin wasn’t going to do it with me.
就是Kevin没能和我一起
Suddenly, I just felt alone.
一刹那间，我觉得很孤独
I think Kevin probably did, too.
我想Kevin也会有同样的感觉
What a crazy experience this has been.
这是多离奇的一种经历
It crashed down on me
我脑子里翻滚着一个想法
that going to the top without Kevin was gonna be devastating.
如果没有Kevin一起登顶，这事就全砸了。
Just got to get KJ up here now.
要把他弄上来，此刻
So I decided in that moment
所以在那一刻我决定了
that we were going to get to the top together.
我们要一起登顶
-[Brett] What will you do?         你要怎么做？
-Everything I can to help him.     尽全力帮他上来
Yeah. 是的
I’m going to go into full-on support mode.
我准备进入全力支持的模式
[Kevin] That night, we both go back down to the camp.
那一晚，我们都下来到大本营
We were cooking dinner.
做饭
It was real quiet.
周围静悄悄的
And I knew it was this emotional moment for Tommy.
我知道这一刻的Tommy心情激动
But he’s not very good at verbalizing.
但他不善表达
I want to do this thing with you, yeah, it's like ...it's cool, man
我希望和你一起登上去，呃，就是 ...真的挺棒，老弟
I mean, it's awesome but when I take, I just really want you. ...there
Yeah, I do
我意思是，登上去是挺棒，不过，我还是特希望你也在
明白。
Yeah.
是啊，
[Kevin]Tommy just told me, in classic Tommy style,
Tommy 以典型的Tommy 风格跟我说
I don’t care how long it takes for you to get through pitch 15,
我不在意你需要花多久才能通过15绳距
because I can’t imagine a worse outcome
因为我不能想象那个糟糕的结果
than doing this alone.
独自一人去登顶
I don’t want to hold you back, is the thing.
是这样，我不希望你掉在后面
You’re three days from the top now or some shit.
你离开峰顶就三天时间了
[Kevin] It’s a pretty special moment.
这一刻很特殊
I know I can do that pitch.
我知道我能穿过那个绳距
Yeah, for sure.
是呀，肯定的
And I feel like if I can do that pitch, I’d be so fucking psyched
我觉得自己可以完成那个绳距，我就是紧张死
that there’s nothing
没有什么
that’s going to stop me between there and the top.
可以挡在峰顶和那块地方之间
I think that’s true.
我认为就是这样
Just keep stretching. Make sure...
伸展胳膊，确认
I think I need to do some arm lengthening stretches.
我觉得自己需要把胳膊抻的更长
[Kevin] So we decided that I would rest two consecutive days
于是我们决定，我再加两天连贯的休息
so that my skin could heal
等待我皮肤复原
and try again.
然后再尝试
[Long] The idea of Tommy waiting,
Tommy 想出来的这个念头
to risk your own success
冒着自己不成功的限
in the hopes that maybe by some miracle Kevin can do it,
以期待，也许Kevin可以奇迹般完成穿越
that’s a partner right there.
这就是同伴的概念
Coffee for KJ.
为Kevin喝彩
[Long] But there’s no guarantee that Kevin’s ever gonna make it.
但，Kevin能否做到，谁也不能保证
I mean, I thought that Kevin was maybe not going to make it.
我意思是，我认为Kevin也许就是做不到
And I was hoping that,
我也希望
since this had been a dream of Tommy’s
因为这是Tommy长久的梦想
a lot longer than it had been a dream of Kevin’s,
比它也成为Kevin的梦想时间要长的多
that Tommy would find a way to complete this climb.
Tommy可以顺利完成这次攀登
As Tommy’s friend, selfishly,
从Tommy朋友自私的角度
I’m thinking to myself, like,
我自己想
“Kevin, dude, time to throw in the towel and support Tommy.”
Kevin，哥们，是时间去帮助Tommy攀上去
Somebody less gracious than Tommy CaIdwell might have said,
没有Tommy Caldwell那样仁厚的人会这样说
“I’ve got to go on without you.”
虽然没有你，我还是要前行
[Dad] But he was committed to Kevin.
但是他承诺Kevin
“We’re doing this together.”
我们要一起完成
And he wouldn’t have been Tommy if he’d done it any other way.
如果不是这样，那就不是Tommy了
[Reporter 1] This just in. Those two American climbers...
进入报道。两位美国攀岩者
-[Re porter 2] Kevin Jorgeson.
-[Reporter 3] Kevin Jorgeson.
[Reporter 4] Stuck for seven straight days.
连续七天时间卡壳了
[Reporter 5] CaIdwell determined to wait...
Tommy Caldwell 决定等待
[Reporter 6] One of them refusing to move higher
他们其中一人拒绝独自登高
without his partner stuck below.
如果他卡壳的搭档无法上去的话
So will they make it?
所以，他们能成功吗？
Can you imagine? This really is no joke.
你可以想象吗？这不是开玩笑
[Kelly] The media started to sound like a tabloid.
媒体开始像小报一样八卦起来
Is Jorgeson spoiling Tommy’s dreams?
Kevin 会不会毁了Tommy的梦想？
[Reporter 7]  Down below, the crowd is waiting and watching.
山底下，人群在等待又观望
[Kevin] Hey, Tommy, what’s the weather look like?
嗨，Tommy， 天气怎么样？
Oh, wait. That’s right, you dropped your phone.
哦，等等，对了，你把手机弄丢了
Dropped my phone last night.
昨晚丢的
I had my chest pocket unzipped. It just fell out.
我的胸兜拉链开了，手机掉出去了。
Hopefully, I didn’t kill anybody down there.
希望没砸到下面的谁
I’d heard that Tommy dropped his phone, and I said,
我听到Tommy 掉了手机的事儿，我就说
“Did he really drop his phone?
他真的掉了手机？
“Or is he just saying, don’t call me anymore?”
还是，他意思是，别电话我了
So fed up with the media circus.
被一堆媒体围住
I think he didn’t drop it.
我觉得他不是掉了手机
He threw it off.
他是扔了手机
Yup. Guess we’ve got to just enjoy the view now.
好吧，猜猜我们现在是不是应该欣赏下风景呢
[Kevin] Over the next few days,
之后的几天
Tommy was content right where we were,
Tommy 满足于我们所处的位置
for however long it was going to be.
也不管还需要多久
He’s just stoked to be up there,
他就是稳稳在上面
and it’s no big deal if it takes another rest day or two
再花个一天、两天，也不是大事儿
or three or five or whatever.
或三天、五天，管它去呢
[Tommy] Yeah, I feel like I’ve just been appreciating things
是呀，我感觉我正在欣赏
a little bit more the last few days.
比过去几天更会欣赏周边了
Ah, sun. 噢，太阳出来了
[Branch] Tommy basically said, “No hurry. I’m patient.”
Tommy 基本就是表述道：不急，我耐心极了
They’re going to get through it. Don’t freak out.
他们会通过的。别一惊一乍的
Don’t worry about the rest of the world that’s watching.
别管那个盯着你的世界
Let’s tune them out. It’s just you and me.
我们忘了他们。就关注你我
It became the two of them.
这就变成了两个搭档的世界
I think I have to try to front-step more,
我在想，要不要试试前跨步多一点
because when it comes time to step on that middle foot,
因为轮到走中间步伐时
I can’t front-step it or in-step it cos this foot’s in the way.
我就做不到前跨步，或者是叠跨步，因为这只脚挡住了路
A couple of your falls last time
上回，你摔下来的几次
were just cos you couldn’t find that right foot.
就是你没能找到放脚的正确位置
So even if it’s a little bit harder, it’s going to be better.
所以，即使更难，其实也会更好些
[Kevin] Tommy’s attitude helped take a bit of the pressure off.
Tommy的态度，帮助把压力卸去不少
But I was still gonna have to do the hardest thing I’ve ever done
但是，还是需要自己去完成平生最难的事
for this to end well.
去得到一个好结果
[TV] Trying to make history
试图开创历史
on one of the hardest climbs in the world.
这是世界上最难的一攀
TJ, what’s the story?
进展如何？
[TJ]Here’s the story.
故事在这儿
I’m only about 30 feet up, and I’ve called my momma twice.
我才上升了30英尺，已经给我妈打过两次电话了
Airight? Can you imagine?
好吧，你可以想象吗？
I’m on what’s called a portaledge
我正在所谓的悬空帐篷里
that’s secured to this wall.
它扣在墙里
These two climbers are using one of these
他们两位攀岩者就是用这法子
secured to a flat surface.
扣出一块平整的面
They’re having to sleep on one of these things,
他们要睡在这平面上
for weeks possibly, trying to make an impossible climb.
或许，好几个星期。这样来完成不可能的攀岩
And me? I have holds here I can use to climb the wall.
我呢，我抓住这儿就可以爬墙了
[Reporter] Scaling the jagged cliff known as El Capitan...
沿着崎岖的El Capitan的悬崖而上........
[Becca] Who is that, Fitz?
Fitz，这是谁呀？
-Daddy. -[Becca]Daddy.
爹爹。。。。爹爹
Getting on the airplane.
登机了
Fitz and I have been home
我和Fitz在家里
waiting for our moment to get on a plane and get out here.
等着飞机过来的时候
And it’s finally come. We’re here.
终于到了。我们来啦
Hey, Fitz, do you see way up high on El Cap?
嗨，Fitz，你能看到El Cap上面的路吗？
-Yeah. 能
-Yeah? Can you see Daddy? 能呀？那你能看到爹爹吗？
[Tommy] After failing for so many years,
这么多年，有多次摔下来的时候
there was times when I definitely felt like giving up.
我肯定有过放弃的想法
But it was actually Becca who helped me to keep going.
但Becca一直鼓舞我走下去
[Becca] Seeing him in his element,
看到他进入状态
I saw this focus and this purpose.
我看到这种专注和目标
I really respected him.
我尊重他
And we fell in love.
也彼此相爱
[Tommy] Becca became my biggest supporter.
Becca 成了我最大的支持者
[Becca] We got married.
我们结婚了
And then we got pregnant shortly after.
很快就怀孕了
Hi.
[Tommy] We had a little boy named Fitz.
有了一个男孩 ， Fitz
[Becca] Hi. Fitz.
[Tommy] The first day that I had this little baby in my arms,
当我第一次手抱这个小宝贝时
I was overcome with the emotion.
真是激动万分
I thought, how am I going to be a good example to Fitz?
我在想，怎样做Fitz的榜样？
How great it is to be a CaIdwell boy.
成为Caldwell家的孩子真是很棒
[Becca] Tommy had always viewed his dad as a superhero,
Tommy 一直把父亲看成是超级英雄
and he wanted to be a superhero for Fitz.
他也期待自己成为Fitz的超级英雄
[Tommy] I wanted Fitz to look at me with that same sort of awe.
我希望Fitz看着我的时候，也用一种起敬的眼神
I wanted to show Fitz how to be passionate...
我想要展示给Fitz如何具有热诚
Boom! 拼
...and how to dream big.
....... 如何怀有大梦想
He already does.
他已经学会了
[Tommy] The Dawn Wall embodied that.
黎明墙就是象征
And so it made me want it even more.
所以它令我更加渴望
[Becca] I told him, you can’t stop now.
我和他说，你不能现在就停下来
You have to do everything to make this happen.
你要去尽力实现它
[Tommy] One, two, three, four, five.
[Kevin] Sometimes you zoom out
有时，你退出来
and you think about what a process it’s been,
去想，这是一个怎样的过程
this wild six-year journey with Tommy.
和Tommy在一起的狂野六年征程
[Becca] Did Kevin start already?
Kevin已经出发了吗？
[Kevin] And now here we are
现在我们来了
at the moment of truth.
一个真实的时间
[Gail] And we’ve just been mesmerized.
我们像被催眠了
Hard to put into words something so big.
难以用言语形容
He’s not going to give up.
他不会放弃的
[Tommy] I couldn’t imagine
我无法想象
what he must have been going through at that moment.
那一刻他经历什么样的心情
[Kevin]I don’t remember the first 50 feet of that pitch.
我都记不得绳距最初的50尺
[Tommy I watched him go into the section
看着他走到那一块地方
where he had fallen so many times.
那块他摔下去N次的地方
I just hold my breath.
我摒住呼吸
[Kevin] You pull as hard as you can.
尽力拉着自己
Move your feet.
移动脚步
Argh 啊
You’re just trying not to tip over backwards.
脚尖必须尽力不往后移
Put the heel on.
把足跟拉上
Slide the hand up.
手掌翻上去
Take the heel off.
放下足跟
Drop the right hand in.
放入右手
Heel back on.
回进足跟
Left hand down.
左手放下
Heart rate starts to go up.
心律加快
[Tommy] My adrenaline starts going cos he’s still hanging on
我的肾上腺素都升高起来，因为他还挂在那儿
in this place that he had fallen so many times.
挂在这块他摔倒N次的地方
[Tommy] Yeah, Kevin!
不错，Kevin
Yeah! 耶呼
Yes! 对了
[Crowd cheering]
[Tommy] Watching him do it, I was just awestruck.
眼望他成功，我都肃然起敬了
I was like, I can’t believe that just happened.
我就是，嗯，我不敢相信刚才发生的
He did it.
他成功了
Freaking guy actually did this thing, right?
崩溃孩子终于成功了，对不对？
You’re like, “What?”
你表现成: 啥？
[Reporter 1]   After seven days,
七天以后
Jorgeson got past the most difficult...
Jorgeson 终于穿越过
[Reporter 2]Past the toughest section of the climb.
攀岩中最艰难的部位
[Branch] Yes, he made it.
是的，他成功了
And now it’s upward.
剩下来就是往上进发
And you start thinking, are his fingers OK? Can he do 16, 17?
你也会想，他手指还行吗？ 能不能穿过16、17 绳距
Is this over yet?
这完了吗？
[Kevin] I had just finished the hardest pitch of my life,
我才完成了一生中最难的绳距
and I couldn’t even celebrate.
还不到庆祝的时候
I just need to catch up.
要追赶上去
[Long] The next pitch is this big Dyno
下一绳距就是大大的Dino 绳距
that’s so hard that Tommy can’t do it,
即使当时Tommy都没能做到的那个绳距
he’s got to climb around it.
他是绕圈上去的
[Kevin] There’s no way in hell
没一点儿门
that I’m going to try Tommy’s crazy loop pitch.
我会去试试Tommy那个怪异的环形绳距
So that same night I start trying the 8 and 1/2 foot Dyno.
所以，同一个夜里，我开始尝试 Dyno 绳距的
Argh! 啊啊
[Groaning]
Yeah! 耶哈
[Long] Kevin, through some kind of magic or levitation,
Kevin，依靠某种神奇或者是浮力
actually does this Dyno that Tommy was never able to do.
居然用Tommy没法完成的动作，把Dyno 拿下来了
-[Tommy] So good. 棒极了
-[Reporter 1] Tonight, Kevin... 今晚，Kevin
[Reporter 2]...now just a few hundred feet behind Caidwell.
只落在Tommy Caidwell后面几百英尺了
[Kevin] All these hard pitches just keep coming.
后面的超难绳距一一露面
17. 18. 19.
[Groansl
[Tommy] It was like a fight to the death.
它就像是与死神的搏斗
-[Kevin] Oh, no.不要
-[Brett] Rock! 岩块呀
That is a bad hold to rip off.
抓握错误，就功亏一篑
Oh, man. 呕，老兄
[Tommy]I think it’s a lot harder now.
我想现在还是挺难的
That didn’t take him too long to figure it out.
他没多久就明白了
[Brett] Nice, KJ! 赞一个，Kevin
[Tommy] It’s just a little more tension.
有点紧张感
Like we need more of that on this route.
好比我们在这条路径上需要这些似的
[Kevin] The last pitch getting to Wino Tower,
到距离Wino Tower前最后的绳距时
this crazy fog came in.
起了诡异的浓雾
[Tommy] Kevin sends this pitch right now,
Kevin 立刻出发了
he’s going to be caught up with me.
他要赶上我
[Kevin]Yes! 是了
[Tommy] Nice one, Kevin. 好好好，Kevin
[Kevin]I just remember seeing Tommy at the anchor
我还记得在锚角石那里看见Tommy
and having such a huge wash of gratefulness.
被感恩的情绪浸泡着
[Tommy] Oh! I can’t believe we’re here.
真不敢相信我们都在这儿了
So good, man.
太好了，老弟
[Kevin] We’re reunited at our high points now.
我们在彼此的最高绳距处汇合了
I can’t believe we did it.
无法相信我们都做到了
Going up from there on out together to the top.
从下往上，一路并肩
[Tommy] Come on, Jorgeson. Come on.
加油，Kevin Jorgeson，加油
[Kevin]  He was sitting on five days’ rest while I caught up.
在我追赶的五天里，他坐歇了五天
Pretty sure he’s going to pull me up the wall today.
今天他肯定要把我拽上岩墙了
[Tommy] From here on it’s just a matter of grinding it out.
从此以后，就是常规性了
So we get up and we stay 300 feet from the top.
所以我们起身后，在离开峰顶300英尺的地方停留住
We wake up this last morning.
最后一个清晨醒来
The sun comes on the Dawn Wall.
阳光照耀在黎明墙面
It hits the top of the Wall first,
阳光首先照到岩墙顶端
and we’re the only thing in Yosemite actually in the sun.
当时我们是优胜美地唯一沐浴在阳光里的人
[Kevin]So happy.
如此快乐
[Tommy] This is a good moment right here.
真是好时光
This is definitely a good moment.
绝对的好时光
[P Music plays]
Does it get any better than this?
还能比这更好吗？
[Tommy] I’m just enjoying my last day
我在享受我最后一天的冲刺
being up here with my friend.
和我的朋友一起
I think we should just stay.
我都想就此停下来
Just cancel the whole thing.
把一切取消
We’re going to camp here for another day.
再花一天露营
[kevin] Living on a wall where everything is so simple
住在岩墙上的生活真是简洁
for 19 days,
19天呐
we were going to miss that experience.
我们会怀念这段经历的
[Mark] Good morning to our viewers.
观众朋友早上好
It’s been an exciting 24 hours here in Yosemite.
刚刚过去的令人激动的24小时，在优胜美地国家公园
[Ranger] Tommy Caidwell and Kevin Jorgeson
Tommy Caidwell 和 Kevin Jorgeson 两位
spent 19 days on the Wall.
度过19天的岩墙生活
There were 15 TV trucks, reporters from all over.
总共有15辆电视台报道卡车，记者们也从四方赶来
There was a webcam.
还有网络摄像机
Millions of people were actually watching this live.
数以百万计的人们直接目睹了这实况
Like a moon landing or something.
几乎类似登月什么了
A lot of their friends and family had come out.
他们各自的家人和朋友也因此而来
A number of people hiked up El Cap the back way,
很多人从El Cap的山后背徒步上来
and you could watch these guys go up the final pitches.
为了亲眼观看这两位完成最后的绳距而上
And they’re cheering them on.
他们正在欢呼
[Becca] I love you! Whoo! 我爱你，喔
It’s gonna be awesome.
真是太棒了
[Beth] Seeing Tommy do the Dawn Wall,
看到Tommy完成夙愿
I was super happy for him.
我为他高兴极了
Just knowing how much was emotionally wrapped up
要知道这包含了多少情感
in the route for him,
对于他，这一路都是
I was really proud of him.
我为他自豪
[Dad] Actually seeing he was going to complete this climb,
亲眼目睹他圆梦攀登
it was just, wow.
就像，哇塞塞
[Reporter 1]  After 19 days,
19天后
Tommy Caidwell pulling himself over the edge of the Dawn Wall.
Tommy Caidwell 在黎明墙的边缘，把自己拽了上去
Followed minutes later by climbing partner Kevin Jorgeson.
几分钟后，他的搭档Kevin Jorgeson也攀爬了上来
[Reporter 2] And the crowd cheered
围观人群欢腾起来
as the two men accomplished a feat many said was impossible.
他们两位完成了众人认为不可能的壮举
[Branch] There aren’t a lot of moments that choke me up
我轻易不会梗咽
in sports anymore. I’ve been doing this too long.
在体育项目上，我很久都不会动感情了
I’ll never forget a scene of them rejoicing.
永远都忘不了他们快乐的那一景
This is the moment that’s been so many years in the making.
为了完成这一刻，花了多少年
Now forever enshrined in history.
现在，可以珍藏在历史里了
[Reporter] Inspiring millions around the world,
鼓舞着全球的人们
even at the White House,
即使是在白宫
where President Obama gave a thumbs up.
奥巴马总统都举赞了
It’s done. It’s done.
完成了，完成了呀
You are shaking like a leaf.
艾，你都像树叶一样发抖了
Are you cold or are you emotional?
你是冷呢还是激动过了？
-I’m emotional. 激动
-OK. 好吧
[Mom] He’s worked so hard for this.
他为此付出了多少
[Kevin] That moment he describes as bittersweet.
那一刻，可以描述为苦乐参半
This whole experience that drove him for so long,
驱动他如此之久的这段经历
it was over.
就此过去了
Anything that you’d like to say about El Cap?
有关El Cap，你想说什么吗？
I’ve totally fallen in love with that piece of rock.
我爱上了那些石头
It’s been a big centerpiece of my life.
它是我生活的中心
And I just feel so thankful every day.
每一天我都感恩
E KEVIN MORBY:
[“I Have Been To The Mountain’9
[Reporter 1]  Tommy and Kevin join us now on SportsCenter.
Tommy和Kevin在体育中心和我们在一起
I know Tommy’s lost his voice a little bit.
我知道Tommy嗓子哑了
[Hoarse voice] It drove me every day for seven years.
七年时间我被它激励
Sorry. 抱歉
What did your first real shower in 19 days feel like?
19天才真正冲澡的感觉如何?
I, like the entire world, was watching you.
我，呃，全球，都在看着你
And I just thought, why?
我在想，为什么？
EPAI Throwing out today’s
first pitch, Kevin Jorgeson.
请开出今天的第一棒，Kevin Jorgeson
[Reporter 2] Tommy Caidwell’s new autobiography, “The Push”.
Tommy Caidwell的新版自传《推动》出来了
You were captured by militants in Kyrgyzstan?
你在吉尔吉斯斯坦被激进分子劫持了？
[Reporter 3]  Turns out
结果是
the militant actually survived the fall.
那个激进分子没有摔死
[Reporter 4]The rebel was put on trial
他被送上了审判庭
and found guilty of terrorism, murder, and kidnapping.
判刑为恐怖行为、谋杀和绑架
I I have been to the mountain
I And I have walked on his shore
I I have seen
I But I can’t see him no more
I have been to the valley
And I have sung all her songs
[Becca] You can do it.你可以做到的
Watch me sing
Look...
Mantle.
Mantle. Come on, try hard.
You’ve got to work hard and focus.
And I have walked
on his shore... 5
You can do it.
You’re working really hard.
Focus.
Come on, Fitz. You got it.
You can do it. Come on, buddy.
Come on.
Remember, push up strong.
Yeah.
Don’t forget to breathe.
Come on. Yeah.
Try hard. Try hard.
Come on, Fitz.
You got it. Yeah.
Way to focus in.
Good perseverance.
Whoo!
Nice mantle, buddy.
High five.
Boom!